<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Christian practice described by way of essay upon the life of our Saviour by Stephen Skynner ...</title>
            <author>Skynner, Stephen.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1693</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 151 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 81 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2013-12">2013-12 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A60331</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing S3946</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R1647</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">12627469</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 12627469</idno>
            <idno type="VID">64677</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A60331)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 64677)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 334:18)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>Christian practice described by way of essay upon the life of our Saviour by Stephen Skynner ...</title>
                  <author>Skynner, Stephen.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[16], 144 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed for Daniel Brown ...,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1693.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>"Imprimatur, Novemb. 17, 1692 C. Alston"</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in Bodleian Library.</note>
                  <note>Marginal notes.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Jesus Christ --  Example.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2011-07</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-07</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-06</date>
            <label>Colm MacCrossan</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-06</date>
            <label>Colm MacCrossan</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-02</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:64677:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:64677:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>Chriſtian Practice DESCRIBED, By WAY of ESSAY UPON THE Life of our Saviour. <hi>By</hi> STEPHEN SKYNNER, Rector of <hi>Buckland</hi> in <hi>Hertfordſhire,</hi> and late Fellow of <hi>Trinity-College</hi> in <hi>Cambridg.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <floatingText xml:lang="eng" type="license">
                  <body>
                     <p>IMPRIMATUR,</p>
                     <closer>
                        <date>
                           <hi>Novemb.</hi> 17. 1692.</date>
                        <signed>C. Alſton.</signed>
                     </closer>
                  </body>
               </floatingText>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>LONDON:</hi> Printed for <hi>Daniel Brown,</hi> at the <hi>Black Swan</hi> and <hi>Bible</hi> without <hi>Temple-Bar.</hi> MDCXCIII.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="preface">
            <pb facs="tcp:64677:2"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:64677:2"/>
            <head>THE PREFACE.</head>
            <p>IT is a good Obſervation, That nothing has made more ATHEISTS in the World, than Superſtition. For though Immorality has certainly too great a ſhare in this, yet may <hi>that</hi> be reckoned in one reſpect not altogether ſo dangerous to Religion, as the other: Immorality being ſo contrary to Nature's Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctates, that all who are not extremely blinded by Vicious Habits, are apt to ſee into the
<pb facs="tcp:64677:3"/>Deformities of it; and ſo it ſerves but as a Foil to ſet off the Beauty of Religion; like thoſe <hi>Hereſies</hi> which the Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtle ſays, <hi>muſt come, that they who are approved may be made ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nifeſt.</hi> Whereas Superſtition defaces Religion it ſelf, as much as in it lies; repre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſenting it in ſuch horrid and ridiculous ſhapes, that <hi>Standers<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by</hi> are rather apt to think it a meer Invention of men, than that a Wiſe and Gracious God ſhould be the Author of ſuch Extravagancies. And the De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſign of this Treatiſe therefore is, to remove thoſe Prejudices which Superſtition has raiſed in mens minds, by ſetting a true Copy of Religion before their eyes.</p>
            <pb facs="tcp:64677:3"/>
            <p>This I thought could no ways better be done, than by following Chriſt himſelf, that great <hi>Maſter,</hi> who was the <hi>wiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom of his Father, and the expreſs image of his perſon;</hi> a main part of whoſe buſineſs it was, to reſtore Religion to its Native Purity, by preſenting the O<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riginal Pattern of it to us, in his own Doctrine and Exam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple: And to <hi>his</hi> Life therefore I have confined my ſelf, with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out referring to any other pla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces almoſt of Scripture. Not but that I pay a like Deference to every other part of God's Word; but I ſuppoſed, that whatever I found in our Savi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>our's Life or Doctrine, was ſufficiently perfect of it ſelf;
<pb facs="tcp:64677:4"/>and I was unwilling to ſwell the Piece to a greater bulk than was proper in this way of writing, by bringing in every Text that might ſeem pertinent to my purpoſe: For which reaſon alſo it is not to be expected that many parti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cular Objections ſhould be formally anſwered here; Tho beſides the general ones which I have ſpoke largely to, I think I have touched upon moſt of the others that are a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny thing material in our Savi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>our's Life. And I know of none in any other part of Scri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pture, but what may eaſily enough be reconciled with the Doctrines here delivered.</p>
            <pb facs="tcp:64677:4"/>
            <p>I expect not that ſome per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons ſhould much approve of what I have done; and I think I have little reaſon to be con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerned at it, conſidering what ſort of people I ſuppoſe them chiefly to be. Our Saviour himſelf Preached Three years to the World, we know, and his very Adverſaries were for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ced to confeſs, That <hi>never man ſpake as he ſpake;</hi> yet neither could the Powers of his Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vine Eloquence, nor his Mira<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cles, make any conſiderable impreſſions upon the <hi>Phariſees</hi> hearts. And it is little to be wondred at therefore, if hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man Labours prove altoge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther fruitleſs upon ſuch per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons. But there are many o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers,
<pb facs="tcp:64677:5"/>I preſume, to whom this Work may be of good uſe, as well for driving out ſome Melancholly Fears and Scruples, whereby well-mean<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing people are apt to be diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>couraged in the Practice of Religion; as for ſilencing thoſe unjuſt Cavils, of its lay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing ſlaviſh and <hi>unmanly</hi> Impo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſitions upon men, which pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phane perſons are wont to bring againſt it.</p>
            <p>Nor do I apprehend the leaſt danger of having this Piece cenſured by any wiſe un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prejudiced perſon, as giving Countenance to Irreligion, whatever weak or brain-ſick people may think of it: For I know of nothing I have
<pb facs="tcp:64677:5"/>mentioned in it, but what I have good ground for from our Saviour's Doctrine and Example: And I am willing to be reckoned among the Ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vocates for Profaneneſs, if any thing that Chriſt ſaid or did, tended that way. I confeſs I have endeavoured what I was able, to imitate the skilful Muſician here, in not ſtraining the Duties of Religion to too high a pitch: For tho they make the greateſt noiſe when they are moſt rai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed, and ſo pleaſe the Vulgar beſt; yet the Sweetneſs and Harmony that is proper to them, is loſt by this to every judicious Ear. Tho neither have I been leſs cautious of
<pb facs="tcp:64677:6"/>ſlackning the ſtrings of Duty too much. And I am confi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dent men will find as little Encouragement here for looſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs of Manners, as for an over-rigid Severity.</p>
            <p>If ſome think it neceſſary to aim at greater Perfection in many Duties than is here re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quired, (I mean <hi>that</hi> which ſuch call <hi>Perfection</hi>) a God's Name let them do it. Their Zeal may be uſeful in ſome reſpects, tho it wants not ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veral Inconveniencies: And the time may come one day, when God will ſay to them, as he does by the Prophet, <hi>Who required theſe things at thy bands?</hi> But if the generality of the world be not able to
<pb facs="tcp:64677:6"/>run ſo faſt in the Courſe of Religion as theſe men do, there is no need ſure of diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>couraging them from trying to walk: Eſpecially, when Chriſt has given us ſuch grounds to belive, That a ſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber diligence in keeping God's Commands, will carry a man as ſoon to Heaven, as the moſt Furious Drivings of men of more Zeal than Underſtand<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing. Nor do I think there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore, that ſuch deſerve leſs of Religion, who recommend it to men of Senſe in Rational ways, as a thing eaſie and na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tural to them, through the Aſſiſtance of God's Grace, than others, who value them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves ſo much upon moving
<pb facs="tcp:64677:7"/>the Affections of common people by undue heightning of things, and make as if there were no Religion but what is next to Impoſſibilities.</p>
            <p>I was loth to interrupt my Method by any long Digreſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion, and therefore reſerved the Diſcourſe concerning the <hi>Phariſees</hi> Hypocriſy, for an Appendix; which I think I need make no Apology for adding, as being ſufficiently pertinent to my main Deſign. For by ſeeing here what it is our Saviour ſo often con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demns the <hi>Phariſees</hi> for, we may the better underſtand our own Duty. And indeed, our Saviour had ſo much to do with the <hi>Phariſees</hi> in all his
<pb facs="tcp:64677:7"/>Diſcourſes, that a man can ſcarce apprehend the Force and Tendency of many of his Precepts, without being rightly informed in the Nature and Qualities of that ſort of people, of which Hypocriſy made ſo great a part. How<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ever, if better Judgments diſapprove the Notion I have gone upon, I hope there is no harm done. It is no Article of Faith, believe the Point which way you will. And if it be any ways of dangerous Conſequence to Religion, I am ſure it is much more ſo in the common Notion, than in the way that I have explain'd it.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="table_of_contents">
            <pb facs="tcp:64677:8"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:64677:8"/>
            <head>The CONTENTS.</head>
            <list>
               <item>
                  <hi>INtroductory Conſiderations touch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing our Saviour's Life and Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrine in General,</hi> Sect. 1, 2, 3.</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Our Saviour's Life and Doctrine in Ceremonial Reſpects: And here,</hi>
               </item>
               <item>Sect. 4. <hi>Of Ceremonies more generally.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>Sect. 5. <hi>Of Reverence in outward Worſhip.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>Sect. 6. <hi>Of the Sabbath or Lord's Day.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>Sect. 7. <hi>Of Faſting</hi>
               </item>
               <item>Sect. 8. <hi>Of other acts of Mortification.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Our Saviour's Life and Doctrine in re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpect of Piety towards God. And here,</hi>
               </item>
               <item>Sect. 9. <hi>Of Faith.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>Sect. 10, 11. <hi>Of the Love of God.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>Sect. 12. <hi>Of Prayer.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>Sect. 13. <hi>Of appropriating due por<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions of time to God's Service.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>Sect. 14. <hi>Of Repentance.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Our Saviour's Life and Doctrine in reſpect of Duties relating to our ſelves: And here,</hi>
               </item>
               <item>Sect. 15. <hi>Of regulating our Paſſions aright.</hi>
               </item>
               <pb facs="tcp:64677:9"/>
               <item>Sect. 16. <hi>Of Temperance.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>Sect. 17. <hi>Of Chaſtity.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>Sect. 18, 19. <hi>Of moderating our De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſires towards earthly things.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>Sect. 20. <hi>Of Pride or Vain-glory.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Our Saviour's Life and Doctrine in reſpect of Duties relating to our Neighbour: And here,</hi>
               </item>
               <item>Sect. 21. <hi>Of theſe Duties in general.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>Sect. 22. <hi>Of Faithfulneſs in Dealing.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>Sect. 23, 24. <hi>Of Mercy or Forgive<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs of Injuries and Debts.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>Sect. 25. <hi>Of Charity.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>Sect. 26. <hi>Of not being angry without juſt cauſe.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>Sect. 27. <hi>Of not judging.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>An Objection anſwered concerning the Primitive Chriſtians Practice,</hi> Sect. 28, 29, 30, 31.</item>
               <item>Sect. 32. <hi>Another Objection anſwered.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>Sect. 33. <hi>A Third Objection anſwered.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>Sect. 34. <hi>The Concluſion.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>An Appendix concerning the Hypo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>criſy of the</hi> Phariſees.</item>
            </list>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="tract">
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:64677:9"/>
            <head>Chriſtian Practice Deſcribed by Way of ESSAY UPON THE LIFE of our SAVIOUR.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">W</seg>Hen I conſider the Life of our Savi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>our, I am no leſs charm'd with the Sweetneſs and Simplicity of his Character, than the admirable Pi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ety of it. And it is no ſmall Evidence to <hi>me</hi> of the Truth of what he de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clared himſelf to be, to find ſo much of true Holineſs in every thing he ſaid or did, mingled with ſo little Oſtentation of Sanctity. Im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſtors are wont to raiſe Credit
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:64677:10"/>to themſelves by different Me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thods. Theſe will take a Form of Godlineſs upon them, which ſhall outdo the Original it ſelf ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny times; but which, like moſt Counterfeits, is found out by no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing more, than that it goes be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>yond Nature; it has too much of Varniſh and Affectedneſs in it to be ſincere. The ſhew of Religion is much more to theſe, than the Subſtance: And ſo it is not ſo much thoſe Duties that are moſt Excel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lent in themſelves, or that God re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quires moſt, but thoſe that are moſt Popular and Plauſible in the Eye of the World, that ſuch chiefly mind. Juſtice and Charity are undoubted<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly Vertues of high Eſteem in God's ſight; and I know of none that our Saviour preſſes more earneſtly. But what a poor noiſe do theſe make among the Vulgar, compared with long Prayers, and Mortifications, and high Flights of Zeal, and Scrupu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>louſneſs about indifferent Matters?
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:64677:10"/>It is theſe laſt chiefly that deno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minate Men <hi>Precious</hi> in common Peoples thoughts: And here there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore the Hypocrite places his ſole Diligence. No matter how groſs his Failings may be in other points. The ſplendor of theſe ſhall dazle peoples Eyes ſo, as ſcarce to let them behold their other Defects. And the very <hi>Name</hi> therefore of a Perſon thus qualified, we find ſuffi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cient many times to ſanctify the moſt Unrighteous action.</p>
            <p n="2">2. Our Saviour had certainly great Reaſon to conform his Life and Doctrine to this way of Pra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctice, had it been Convenient in it ſelf. For this was a ſort of Reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gion more eſpecially in Vogue in his Time. The Phariſees, every one knows, what Zealous Profeſſors they were of it. Never was great<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er Perfection in Holineſs than theſe men might juſtly Boaſt of, if mor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tified Looks and Behaviour were
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:64677:11"/>the <hi>great things</hi> required of us by God. The Sun it ſelf might ſeem ſpotted,
<note place="margin">Mat. 11.19.</note> in theſe reſpects, compa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red with their Purity. Whence we find them taking great Offence at our Saviour for his Freedom in Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſe, as ſavouring much of Looſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs and Unſanctifiedneſs, they thought. And no queſtion there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore, as this prejudiced them very much againſt hearkning to what he taught, ſo had he but humoured them a little in their Affected Pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciſeneſs, wherein they laid the <hi>main ſtreſs</hi> of Religion, it would no leſs have recommended his Perſon and Doctrines to them. By which means he would have gained the Common people alſo of Courſe, theſe being wholly at the others Beck. The Phariſees were not blinder Guides to <hi>theſe,</hi> than <hi>thoſe</hi> were blind Fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowers and Admirers of the Phari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſees. But however advantageous it might have proved to Religion, at that time, to humour the Phariſees
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:64677:11"/>in <hi>this,</hi> yet was not our Saviour to be wrought upon, even by that <hi>weightieſt</hi> Conſideration, to do it, ſo much as by his Example. Our Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viour in all likelihood conſidered here, that he was no <hi>Private</hi> Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon. His Life was to be a Pattern for all Ages to imitate. And it was by no means fit therefore, for the ſake of one Perverſe Generation, to lay ſuch an unneceſſary Burden upon the Conſciences of the whole World, as his Example muſt have proved, had he complied with the Phariſees in any of their Formal ways of Sanctity.</p>
            <p n="3">3. And we find nothing of this therefore in our Saviour's Life; no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing of the Sourneſs of a Phariſai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cal Leaven in all his Character. His Converſation is every where eaſy and natural; as far diſtant from a Puritanical Niceneſs, as from the Severity of the Cloiſter. It is holy and blamleſs in every part; and yet
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:64677:12"/>ſo accommodated to our Humane Eſtate, that we have no more rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon to complain of want of due <hi>Liberty</hi> in it, than of <hi>Perfection.</hi> And would ſome Perſons conſider it aright, there can nothing more <hi>E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ffectual</hi> be imagined, for removing their Prejudices againſt Religion. Thoſe whom the ſtarchtneſs of a Phariſaical Carriage does juſtly Nauſeate, and who perhaps find as little Deſire, as Ability in them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves, to imitate ſuch a Behaviour, would they but look into their Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viour's Example, would find every thing in it ſo contrary to <hi>this,</hi> as muſt ſoon make Religion the ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ject, not of their Scorn, but their Envy. For there is nothing of the <hi>Saint</hi> there, but what compleats <hi>the Man;</hi> and what is fully as ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſary to make us happy, as rati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>onal Creatures. A man may be Religious, according to this, with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out intrenching upon the Offices of Civility, or denying himſelf any
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:64677:12"/>reaſonable Comfort; without do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing any thing beneath the Honour of a Wiſe or a Great Perſon. And what<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ever ſhew of Holineſs ſome may make, by pretending to more than this, it is at beſt no other than to go beyond <hi>the Rule.</hi> I ſpeak not this however in relation to our Saviour's extraordinary Miſſion, but with reſpect only to the <hi>Common</hi> Duties of Religion. As our Saviour was a Prophet ſent from God, and as he was the Great Mediator beſides, there are ſeveral Acts recorded of him, peculiar to thoſe Offices, which are quite out of the ordinary Road of Life: ſuch was his Preaching in the Deſerts, and in the High<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ways, and his Miracles. The for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mer of which it is no leſs abſurd to think our ſelves bound to imitate, now Chriſt has appointed a Regu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lar Miniſtry in his Church, than it is impoſſible to practiſe the latter of them. But for the ordinary Duties of Piety and Vertue, our Saviour's
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:64677:13"/>Example is every where <hi>obligatory</hi> to us. And this is ſo excellent in it ſelf, that every Wiſe man would chuſe to follow it, though God had laid no Obligation upon him. To conſider it in the moſt remarkable Circumſtances of it.</p>
            <p n="4">4. Look upon our Saviour's Life in Ceremonial reſpects, and you will find nothing of needleſs Scru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pulouſneſs or Superſtition there. He is for preſerving <hi>Order</hi> and <hi>Decency</hi> in God's Church as much as any; though not for encouraging every vain Cuſtom or Rite, which ſome would impoſe under the Name of Religion. When the <hi>Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nons</hi> of the Church he lived under required it, he <hi>conforms</hi> without <hi>Diſpute</hi> in indifferent matters. The Feaſt of Tabernacles may well ſeem as <hi>beggerly an Element,</hi> as any amongſt thoſe the Apoſtle calls <hi>ſuch;</hi> and no queſtion it was deſigned by God, as a fitter Entertainment for
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:64677:13"/>the groſs Plebeian Humours of his <hi>Servants</hi> the <hi>Jews,</hi> than for his <hi>Son.</hi> Yet did not Chriſt diſdain to appear at <hi>that,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Joh. 7.10.</note> no more than he did at the Feaſt of Dedication,
<note place="margin">John 10.22.</note> which was a Feaſt purely of Humane Inſtituti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on. It was Argument enough to him for obſerving <hi>that,</hi> that it was ordained by the Church of which he was a Member; and he was not ſo ſqueamiſh here, as to queſtion the Authority of his Church in conſtituting ſo innocent a Right; though it might ſeem an En<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>croachment upon God's Prerogative under the <hi>Jewiſh</hi> Theocracy, and though it was adding weight ſtill to that burden which the <hi>Jews</hi> be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore were ill able to bear.</p>
            <p>And what he thus practiſed him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf, he is very expreſs in command<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing his Diſciples to imitate him in. <hi>The Scribes and Phariſees,</hi> ſays he,
<note place="margin">Mat. 23.2, 3.</note> 
               <hi>ſit in Moſes's ſeat; all therefore what<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ever they bid you obſerve, that obſerve and do.</hi> There could nothing be
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:64677:14"/>ſaid more <hi>full</hi> than this, for eſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bliſhing the Church's Rights in matters of Ceremony; that in eve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry thing of this nature, not plainly ſinful, (for thus far the Command muſt of neceſſity be reſtrained, and to reſtrain it further is to deſtroy the Force of it), our Saviour's Will is, The Governours of the Church ought to be obeyed. For ſure the <hi>Scribes</hi> and <hi>Phariſees</hi> at this time, were blind and corrupt enough to be excluded this Privilege, if ever it were convenient the Governors of the Church ſhould be ſo. Not that our Saviour warrants any Church by this, in conſtituting fooliſh or burthenſome Rites to no purpoſe; for Tyranny is hateful to God in <hi>all</hi> Governments; and more eſpecially to be ſure in ſuch, where the Souls of men are concerned: And our Saviour therefore often <hi>proteſts</hi> againſt the <hi>Pharifees</hi> arbi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trary Uſurpations, in clogging God's Service with vain and need<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſs
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:64677:14"/>Ceremonies. But in regard Tyranny was ever reckoned better than no Government at all, there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore does our Saviour command his Diſciples to be ſubject to the Gover<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nors of the Church in all <hi>Indiffe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rent</hi> matters, rather than Schiſm and Diſorder ſhould happen in his Church, by people's obeying no farther than juſt what they pleaſe. Though here he diſtinguiſhes be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>twixt the Publick Sanctions of the Church, ratified by juſt Authority, and the Opinions of private Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctors, embraced only by particular Sects. Of which laſt ſort we muſt reckon thoſe <hi>Traditions of the El<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders,</hi> ſo frequently mentioned by Chriſt, to be, if we ſuppoſe him conſiſtent with himſelf (with Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verence be it ſpoken). For <hi>theſe</hi> he neither obſerved himſelf, nor does he adviſe his Diſciples to pay any regard to them, as being whol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly unobligatory in themſelves, and for the moſt part very vain and ſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perſtitious:
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:64677:15"/>Particularly that about waſhing of hands before meat; a Cuſtom abuſed to that height of Superſtition among the <hi>Phariſees,</hi> that one of their wiſe Doctors teaches us, To eat with unwaſhen hands is all one as to lye with a Whore. This therefore, and the like Ceremonies, our Saviour ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>glects to comply with himſelf; and he ſcorns the Objection of the <hi>Pha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſees,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Mat. 15.2.</note> in urging the <hi>Tradition of the Elders</hi> againſt his Diſciples, for fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowing his Example in it.</p>
            <p n="5">5. The greateſt Act of Zeal in our Saviour's Life, was ſpent upon <hi>whipping the Buyers and Sellers</hi> out of the Temple.
<note place="margin">John 2.15.</note> Nor is it to be wondred at, to ſee his Indignation rais'd at this rate, upon ſuch an oc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>caſion; Natural Religion teaching us, That the Temples of God ought not to be turned into Markets and Exchanges. If any except at the manner of our Saviour's reforming
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:64677:15"/>this Abuſe, let them conſider the liberty that Prophetick Perſons of old were warranted in by God a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mong the <hi>Jews,</hi> as well as <hi>that</hi> which the Zealots in our Saviour's time were permitted ordinarily by the Magiſtrates to take upon themſelves. Let them conſider likewiſe, that Chriſt's Commiſſion was above all others that God ever gave to men. He acted <hi>as a Son</hi> in God's Houſe, when <hi>Moſes himſelf was but as a Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vant.</hi> Though, not to examine farther into <hi>his</hi> Authority to do this, who had <hi>all Power given him</hi> upon Earth, no queſtion but a Divine Spirit was at the bottom of this Act. And the deſign of it is evi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dently no other, than to ſhew, That God's Honour and the Intereſts of Religion are not a little concerned in outward Reverence and Reſpect. For what elſe could have put the meek and gentle Spirit of Chriſt in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to ſuch a Ferment? It is not to be thought this was done in favour of
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:64677:16"/>the <hi>Jewiſh</hi> Temple or Ceremonies alone: For Chriſt repeated this Act twice,
<note place="margin">Mat. 21.12.</note> and the laſt time, the very Week of his Paſſion. But ſure he would never have been ſo extraor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinary zealous in this matter, at ſuch a time, were it only to ſupport the Credit of the Ceremonial Law a few days, which was now juſt <hi>ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>piring</hi> with his Death. Some in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deed, that reckon nothing too great or glorious for themſelves, count nothing <hi>mean</hi> enough for God. But our Saviour was not of this hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mour; he could behold <hi>the goodly ſtones of the Temple,
<note place="margin">Luk. 21.5.</note> and the gifts wherewith it was adorned,</hi> without crying out with <hi>Judas, Why was this waſte made?</hi> And he could <hi>weep</hi> in proſpect of the Ruins of ſo ſtately an Edifice,
<note place="margin">Luke 19.41.</note> when others would have ſhouted for joy, that proud <hi>Babylon</hi> was falling. Nor did Chriſt pay greater reſpect to God this way in his Temple <hi>made with hands,</hi> than in the Temple of
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:64677:16"/>his <hi>own Body;</hi> for though the great<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs of his Character (being the Eternal Son of God) might juſtly have entituled him to greater free<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom with his Father; yet for our example, when he prayed,
<note place="margin">Luke 22.41.</note> 
               <hi>he kneel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed down,</hi> it is ſaid: Certainly a moſt unanſwerable Reproof to that rude familiarity which many uſe with God in their Devotions. For what ſhall we ſay here? Are we more the <hi>Sons of God</hi> than Chriſt, that we ſhould think it ſeemly for us to <hi>ſit down</hi> before our Heavenly Father, when he <hi>knelt?</hi> Or are we wiſer than he, to think ſuch outward Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verence of no regard in God's e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſteem, when even in a <hi>Garden</hi> upon the <hi>bare ground,</hi> Chriſt made a Conſcience of paying it to him?</p>
            <p n="6">6. We find the <hi>Phariſees</hi> often <hi>at</hi> our Saviour about the Sabbath. And ſome may think it ſtrange, that he who expreſſed ſo great Zeal for the <hi>Sanctuary</hi> of God, ſhould not
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:64677:17"/>ſhow greater concern than he did, for the Honour of his <hi>Sabbaths.</hi> But the caſe betwixt theſe was very different: For the <hi>Jews,</hi> who at this time ſo profanely neglected the Temple, were no leſs ſuperſtitiouſly nice in keeping the Sabbath; and tho a <hi>Whip</hi> were fitteſt to ſcourge their <hi>Profaneneſs,</hi> a <hi>Bridle</hi> was moſt proper to reſtrain their <hi>Superſtition.</hi> Wherefore we may obſerve him holding the Reins <hi>in</hi> here upon eve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry occaſion: He is far from encou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>raging any in a <hi>looſe regard</hi> towards this day; for he conſiders it as a day dedicated to God's Service; and we find him therefore <hi>Preaching</hi> continually upon it in the <hi>Jewiſh Synagogues;</hi>
               <note place="margin">Mark 6.2.</note> to ſhew that one prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cipal Duty of the <hi>Day</hi> is to attend the Publick Worſhip of God; and all the <hi>liberty</hi> he pleads directly for on this day, is only for works of Neceſſity and Mercy. It is in re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpect of <hi>theſe</hi> alone he tells us,
<note place="margin">Mark 2.27, 28.</note> That <hi>the Sabbath was made for man, and
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:64677:17"/>that man is lord alſo of the Sabbath.</hi> Nor does he give the leaſt counte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nance for ſpending this Day upon Recreation or Secular Buſineſs. As ſure it is very hard, ſince God has given us <hi>ſix</hi> days in the week for the benefit of our Bodies, if the <hi>ſeventh</hi> ſhall not be allowed by us to his Glory, and the good of our Souls. Though neither is Chriſt for tying men up upon this Day, to that ſtrictneſs which was enjoined by <hi>Moſes</hi> as a Clog and Puniſhment to the <hi>Jews.</hi> He himſelf was a <hi>Jew,</hi> and as a <hi>Jew</hi> therefore no queſtion he obſerved this Day in all reſpects anſwerable to the <hi>intent</hi> of <hi>Moſes,</hi> though not to the <hi>Phariſees</hi> ſuper<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtitious Gloſſes upon it: But the <hi>Curſe of the Law</hi> which he was <hi>made under,</hi> he deſired not to bring upon any of us: And leſt his Exam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple therefore ſhould be brought in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to preſident, there is no mention made of any <hi>Legal</hi> Obſervances, in reſting from Culinary Affairs, or
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:64677:18"/>the like, which he tied himſelf or his Diſciples up to on this Day. Ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, the whole drift of his Diſcour<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes about this Day, being more to <hi>take off from,</hi> than advance any ſcrupulous Reſt upon it, is a plain Argument of his Deſign to ſet up that more <hi>Rational</hi> Sabbath, which the Primitive Chriſtians afterwards obſerved upon the Lord's Day; when the Sabbath was reckoned, not ſo much a Day of <hi>Reſt,</hi> as a Day of <hi>Good Works.</hi> And inſtead of ſitting ſtill upon it, as the <hi>Pha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſees</hi> did, with frozen hearts, and ſullen dejected looks, Chriſtians thought nothing ſo proper (next to God's Worſhip), as to expreſs their Joy upon it, in making com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fortable Proviſions for themſelves, and for the Poor. We know what <hi>hard words</hi> the Father gave ſuch perſons, who choſe to Faſt upon this Day.</p>
            <pb n="19" facs="tcp:64677:18"/>
            <p n="7">7. Faſting, I think, may well be brought under the <hi>Head</hi> of Cere<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monial Duties: And this is certain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly an excellent Ordinance in it ſelf; there being no means more proper for reſiſting the Devil's Aſſaults, by making us <hi>meek</hi> and <hi>poor in ſpirit,</hi> fit for the Influences of God's Spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit to work upon. And our Saviour therefore is ſo far from diſcounte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nancing this, that he ſays there are <hi>ſome Devils not to be caſt out without it.</hi>
               <note place="margin">Mat. 17.21.</note> And he not only prepared him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf therefore by it,
<note place="margin">Mat. 4.2. Mark 6.16, 17.</note> in order to that grand Conflict he had with the De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vil; but he recommends the uſe of it to his Diſciples, at the ſame time that he cautions them againſt the <hi>Phariſees</hi> way of Faſting: Indeed he is againſt the <hi>Phariſees</hi> Faſts, not only as they had an Hypocritical Air of Pride and Vainglory in them, but as they were reckoned by them a Meritorious Act. For never were higher Aſſerters of the Doctrine of <hi>Merit</hi> by Good Works,
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:64677:19"/>than among theſe <hi>Phariſees.</hi> Whence it was, that to enhanſe the value of this Duty before God, their Faſts were both carried on with greater Strictneſs, and were much more <hi>frequent</hi> than other peoples. Nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther of which is much commend<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed by Chriſt: As to the frequency of their Faſts, our Saviour uſed his Diſciples ſo little to this,
<note place="margin">Mark 2.18.</note> as to make the <hi>Phariſees</hi> think they Faſted not at all. It may ſeem he was not for making this Duty too <hi>common,</hi> but for uſing it only as occaſion requi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red. When ſuch Duties are practi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed of courſe, they are apt to loſe their virtue ſoon, like Phyſick to which mens bodies are accuſtomed. It is the applying them upon great and ſpecial occaſions chiefly, that makes them have due <hi>Operation</hi> up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on mens minds. And though our Saviour therefore tells us, That his Diſciples ſhould practiſe this Duty oftner <hi>when he was gone;</hi>
               <note place="margin">Mark 2.20.</note> this implies not, that it ſhould always be ſo,
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:64677:19"/>but only whilſt the days of Mourn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing (as it were) for the <hi>Bride<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>groom's Departure,</hi> did in an extra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ordinary manner require it: And much leſs does our Saviour commend the <hi>Phariſees</hi> rigid Obſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vance of this Duty; pale looks, and drooping heads, are things per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>haps that <hi>man</hi> may admire people for, but God delights not in. Even in this moſt Mortifying Act of Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligion,
<note place="margin">Mat. 6.17.</note> Chriſt is for <hi>anointing the head,</hi> and <hi>waſhing the face;</hi> for be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>having our ſelves with modeſt ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſions of Chearfulneſs before the World.</p>
            <p n="8">8. This Principle of <hi>Merit</hi> which the <hi>Phariſees</hi> ſo eſpouſed, put them not only upon Faſting at this rate, but upon Whipping themſelves al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſo, and uſing the like acts of Auſte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity, as good Authors report; which is the practice of the <hi>Romaniſts</hi> at this day: And this was a <hi>mighty</hi> work of Supererogation among
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:64677:20"/>them. But our Saviour gives not the leaſt Encouragement to this, ei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther by his Precept or Example. As Whipping is reckoned a part of <hi>Pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nance</hi> by the <hi>Romiſh</hi> Church, we are not ſo unreaſonable to expect to find our Saviour <hi>exerciſing</hi> his Body after this manner, for ſins he never committed; tho as it was reckoned awork of ſuperabundant <hi>Merit,</hi> as well as of <hi>Satisfaction,</hi> by the <hi>Pha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſees,</hi> it may ſeem as proper for him, as any body elſe: But then certainly it is very ſtrange, among ſo many Penitents as came to him for cure of their Sins, that he ſhould never preſcribe this <hi>Method</hi> of let<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting themſelves blood, did he be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieve it of any avail to that end. It's true,
<note place="margin">Luke 18.13.</note> he gives a fair Character of the <hi>Publican's ſmiting upon his breaſt,</hi> when he made Confeſſion of his ſins to God; But what then? That was an Act ſignificant of <hi>True Contriti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on,</hi> and was no leſs natural for per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons in great Trouble of Mind, than
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:64677:20"/>Whipping is fooliſh and unnatural. Nor is <hi>John</hi> the Baptiſt's courſe of life, which the Papiſts inſiſt ſo much upon, any juſt ground for this, or the like Auſterities: For (beſides that there is nothing there of this <hi>Whipping</hi> Practice), <hi>John</hi> the Bap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſt had an extraordinary Call from God to do what he did: He was to come in the <hi>Spirit of Elias,</hi> as a Forerunner of Chriſt, and ſo was to imitate that Prophet in a rough, hardy way of Life: And this, we may ſuppoſe, to repreſent to us, as in an Emblem, the different Tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per betwixt the Law and Goſpel: For <hi>John</hi> the Baptiſt was the laſt Prophet of the old Law, in whom God would ſhew us the Severity of thoſe Precepts which he thought fit to hold the <hi>Jews</hi> under; but which he is pleaſed now to hold his Church no longer to, for the ſake of his Son: Whoſe way of Life therefore was a perfect <hi>Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſe</hi> to that of <hi>John</hi> the Baptiſt.
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:64677:21"/>And indeed, ſuch Auſterities as theſe, when men take them upon themſelves of their own heads, or when they pretend to impoſe them upon others, are no other than ſuch Obſervances as our Saviour points at, when he tells the <hi>Phari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſees,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Mat. 15.9.</note> That <hi>in vain they worſhipped God, teaching for Doctrines the commandments of men.</hi> The <hi>Pha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſees</hi> pretended no ground for them in <hi>their</hi> Law, no more than the Papiſt can well do in <hi>ours.</hi> And though in Charity therefore we condemn them not for ſuch extravagant <hi>Will-Worſhip</hi> as this, yet we rather pity than commend them. Such was our Saviour's Life and Doctrine in reſpect of Ce<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>remonies.</p>
            <p n="9">9. Conſider our Saviour's Life in reſpect of Piety towards God, and you will find as little of <hi>Enthu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiaſm</hi> in it in <hi>that,</hi> as of <hi>Scrupulouſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs</hi> or <hi>Superſtition</hi> in the other re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpect.
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:64677:21"/>Faith is the great foundati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of Piety. And this is a Duty of an extraordinary nature in one reſpect, as the Gift of Prophecy, and the power of working Mira<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cles depend upon it. Though in this reſpect our <hi>Saviour</hi>'s Faith was not <hi>Enthuſiaſtick.</hi> For our <hi>Saviour</hi> real<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly ſhewed the juſt pretences he made to an extraordinary Faith, by the <hi>mighty works</hi> he did; whereas the Faith of Enthuſiaſts produces no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing above the <hi>power of Nature.</hi> And neither was our <hi>Saviour</hi>'s Faith attended with thoſe violent Pertur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bations of mind and body, which Enthuſiaſts are ever poſſeſſed with in their pretenſions to Revelation and Prophecy. But as Faith is an ordinary Duty of Religion, it is only a firm belief in, and reliance upon the Promiſes and Declarations of God, whether with reſpect to Spiritual or Temporal concerns. As to both which, there is nothing our <hi>Saviour</hi> recommends, but what e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>very
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:64677:22"/>wiſe and ſober man both may, and ought to ſubſcribe to. As to Spiritual conceerns, the great Arti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cle of our Faith is, to believe that God will <hi>reward</hi> ſuch in another life, who <hi>diligently ſeek him</hi> in this. And what is there in <hi>that</hi> more, than what the moſt Barbarous Nations have ever conſented in, and which there is nothing more diſhonoura<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble to our Natures than to deny? If we are bound alſo to believe, that the Goſpel of Chriſt propoſes the ſafeſt and beſt way of <hi>ſeeking</hi> God, and ſo of obtaining a future Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward, I ſuppoſe no one that calls himſelf a Chriſtian will think much of having that added to his <hi>Creed.</hi> Nay, and conſidering the excellency of that Teſtimony with which the Goſpel is confirmed, if Chriſtians are alſo required to give their conſents to ſome <hi>Truths</hi> there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in revealed, which are above the power of <hi>Humane reaſon</hi> to com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prehend; I think no man, in <hi>com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:64677:22"/>Modeſty,</hi> can object againſt this: eſpecially whilſt he conſiders withal the vaſt diſproportion betwixt God and us, together with the weakneſs of Humane faculties in diſcerning the Nature Cand auſes even of the moſt common Accidents here be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>low. There are many things in Nature which we <hi>believe,</hi> though we <hi>ſee them not,</hi> and though they ſeem ſomewhat <hi>contrary</hi> to reaſon; ſuch is the Earths hanging upon nothing, in the midſt of the Air, which we have nothing but the power of an Almighty Architect to fly to for the ſolution of; but ſure it is hard to deny that Faith to <hi>Supernatural,</hi> which we give to <hi>Natural</hi> things As to Temporal concerns, the ſum of our Faith is, That God governs the world with the greateſt wiſdom and goodneſs, and ſo that we ought to rely upon his Providence in the uſe of lawful means, without anxious fears or troubles. And this is no other than
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:64677:23"/>a natural Principle, and ſuch as is the great foundation of Happineſs in this life. He that believes this heartily, is at Peace with himſelf in every condition; and the <hi>ſame Peace</hi> which he brings to himſelf by it, he ſuffers the reſt of the World to enjoy. Whilſt ſome whining Hypocrites, that talk of nothing <hi>more</hi> than Faith, and pra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctiſe nothing <hi>leſs</hi> than what Faith directs, are a continual Plague to themſelves and all about them, by needleſs Complaints and Jealouſies. It is a noble Strain of Philoſophy that our Saviour expreſſes himſelf in, about that undiſturbed Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tent which every one ought to quiet his Soul with, in conſiderati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of God's Providence.
<note place="margin">Mat. 6.34.</note> 
               <hi>Take no thought for the morrow, but let the morrow take thought for it ſelf; ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficient for the day is the evil thereof.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="10">10. I ove of God is the moſt <hi>ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nuine</hi> Effect of true Faith. And the
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:64677:23"/>Love of the <hi>Eternal begotten Son</hi> towards <hi>his Father,</hi> we may well think was <hi>ſo</hi> great, as to leave <hi>in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>finitely</hi> behind it every thing that is called by <hi>that</hi> Name. Yet do we ſee little of thoſe Tranſports of Paſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion in his Love, which Myſtical people talk ſo much of; and which make the Love of God a Duty no leſs difficult to be underſtood than practiſed. He tells us indeed in one place,
<note place="margin">John 10.30. John 14.11.</note> That <hi>he and the father were one;</hi> and in another, That <hi>the fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther was in him, and he in the father.</hi> But ſuch places relate to his <hi>Hypo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtatical</hi> Union with the Divine Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture, which it is Blaſphemy for any to pretend to beſides himſelf. And there is little ground therefore from hence, for thoſe extravagant expreſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſions which contemplative <hi>Rhapſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diſts</hi> love to ſpeak in, of being uni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted by Love to the Divine Eſſence, and being <hi>Transfuſed</hi> into God. When chriſt ſpeaks of Love as a Duty incumbent on us, we have no
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:64677:24"/>ſuch Expreſſions as theſe. And to love God then is no more, than to <hi>keep his Commandments</hi> out of a Principle of <hi>Duty</hi> and <hi>Choice,</hi>
               <note place="margin">John 14.21.</note> as we count him a <hi>Being</hi> highly worthy to be ſerved by us before all things. And there is no need of ſtraining our faculties to ſuch Romantick heights, as the people I have been ſpeaking of talk of, to do this. For though our Saviour tells us, that we muſt <hi>love the Lord our God with all our hearts,
<note place="margin">Mark 12.30.</note> and all our ſouls, and all our minds, and all our ſtrength;</hi> What is this more, than to expreſs our Love towards him, in obeying his Commands with readineſs and ſin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerity? As we uſually mean in com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon Speech, when we cry, we will do ſuch a thing with <hi>all our hearts,</hi> that we are diſpoſed with willing<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs and affection to do it. There are no Notions of Divine Love more ſublime, than thoſe we meet with in <hi>Plato</hi> and his Heathen fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowers; from whom it is plain our
<pb n="31" facs="tcp:64677:24"/>
               <hi>Myſtical Divinity</hi> took its Riſe. But ſuch ought to have <hi>ſtrong</hi> Heads, that ſoar aloft, as they did. And if Vulgar Souls are bound to aim at ſuch Contemplative Perfection as theſe talk of, we ſhall want more <hi>Bedlams</hi> than Churches. Nor can I think <hi>that</hi> to be a Perfection in Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligion, which none but Philoſophers, and men that lead the lives of ſuch (I mean Sedentary Contemplative lives) are capable of arriving at. As if God had not the ſame regard to a <hi>poor Labouring man,</hi> that ſtudies diligently to ſerve him in a plain well meaning way, as to the moſt <hi>Speculative</hi> perſon in the world. It is the <hi>meek</hi> and <hi>humble</hi> Soul that Chriſt delights moſt in; and it were well therefore if theſe high Notions did not puff mens minds up with too much Spiritual Pride, to make them deſerve the Character of ſuch perſons.</p>
            <pb n="32" facs="tcp:64677:25"/>
            <p n="11">11. I never met any people in my life that were more unwilling to leave the world, than thoſe who make a <hi>Longing</hi> deſire of enjoying God in Heaven to be a <hi>neceſſary</hi> part of our Love towards him. You ſhall find theſe cling as cloſe to the earth as other people, when Death gives them warning to prepare themſelves for parting with it; they are as peeviſh as others, and inqui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſitive after Remedies, and deſirous to be flattered into good hopes of doing well again, which are certain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly no ſigns of any <hi>extraordinary</hi> For<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wardneſs to go to their <hi>long Homes.</hi> Nor can I ſee Ground of Condemn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing men of this, as long as we find our Saviour himſelf <hi>Sympathizing</hi> with Humane Nature in it. Were there any neceſſity of <hi>ſuch</hi> an in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtance to prove our Love towards God to be ſincere, we might juſtly have expected from Chriſt, a deſire of leaving this world, and being uni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted to God upon <hi>any</hi> Terms. For
<pb n="33" facs="tcp:64677:25"/>what were the Sufferings he was to endure, compared with the <hi>joy that was ſet before him?</hi> But our Saviour deſired not to make himſelf an Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ample of ſuch <hi>Heights</hi> of Love; which (tho viſible in ſome Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phets, and Divinely Inſpired per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons, from their intimate Converſe with God, as well as in ſome Saints and Martyrs immediately before their deaths, for Confirmation of <hi>theirs</hi> and other peoples Faith; yet) in the ordinary Diſpen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſations of Grace are little leſs than impracticable. And there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore when the <hi>Cup</hi> of his Paſſion was preſented to him,
<note place="margin">Mat. 26.39.</note> he ſhrinks back from it, in a natural abhor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rence; and he chuſes rather to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceive the irrevocable Sentence with an act of bare Submiſſion to God's Will, <hi>(Father, not as I will, but as thou wilt)</hi> than any Rapturous Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſions of Longing after God: The ſame which is obſervable in the <hi>whole</hi> Hiſtory of his Death.
<pb n="34" facs="tcp:64677:26"/>But if Chriſt behaved himſelf at this rate, whoſe Faith was ſo <hi>ſtrong,</hi> and conſequently his Love of God ſo <hi>ardent,</hi> What more can be ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pected from us <hi>weak</hi> Creatures? Indeed the <hi>glaſs we ſee through here,</hi> is ſo <hi>dark,</hi> as to Heavenly Things, compared with that which preſents Earthly Objects to us, that if our Bodily Welfare affect us more than the Hopes of Future Happineſs, it may in a great meaſure be excuſed by the different Force of the Ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jects ſtriking upon our Faculties: And therefore it required all the Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guments and Exhortations that the Wiſdom of God (as it were) could invent, to raiſe our Thoughts to a tolerable reliſh and apprehen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion of thoſe glorious things re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vealed in his Word. Wherefore, in ſhort, though the Enjoyment of God in Heaven be certainly the <hi>Great End</hi> of a Chriſtian's hopes, and that which all his actions ought in ſome meaſure to be directed to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards;
<pb n="35" facs="tcp:64677:26"/>yet to propoſe this to our ſelves with <hi>Paſſion</hi> and <hi>Eagerneſs of Deſire,</hi> or ſo as utterly to deſpiſe the Comforts of this World, may well be thought a little above the proportion of the imperfect eſtate of a Chriſtian in this life; being reſerved by God as a main part of that Happineſs which we muſt ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pect in the Bleſſed Viſion above.</p>
            <p n="12">12. Prayer is an excellent ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſion of Piety towards God: And there is nothing recommends this Duty ſo effectually to him, as Fervour of Devotion in it: But then our Saviour ſhews us, that this Fervour conſiſts not (as ſome would have it thought) in wild Geſtures, or loud and paſſionare Exclamations. When he himſelf prayed in the Garden, he <hi>prayed earneſtly,</hi> it is ſaid;
<note place="margin">Luke 22.44.</note> and we may well think his heart was never ful<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ler, than in that bitter Agony, nor conſequently his Affections more
<pb n="36" facs="tcp:64677:27"/>
               <hi>raiſed</hi> than at that time. And yet what is the reſult of this, but that he <hi>fell</hi> meekly <hi>upon his knees three times,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Mat. 26.39, 42, 44.</note> and uttered theſe few gentle words, <hi>Father, if it be thy will, let this cup paſs from me:</hi> And if we conſider <hi>that Prayer</hi> of his which he preſcribed to his Diſciples, both as a <hi>Pattern</hi> to Pray by, and a <hi>Form</hi> to be conſtantly uſed by them, it may ſeem contrived on purpoſe to anſwer the Enthuſiaſts pretences about this Duty: For (not to in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiſt upon its being a Form of Pray<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er) in the firſt place it was ſuch a Form as was very ſhort, conſiſting of but Six Petitions, and thoſe com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prehended in few Words: He was not for the way of ſome people, who meaſure their Prayers more by the <hi>Hour-glaſs</hi> than their <hi>Wants.</hi> He expoſes it as an <hi>Heatheniſh Cu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtom</hi> to uſe <hi>vain Repetitions,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Mat. 6.7.</note> and im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pertinent Length in Prayer. Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſides this, it is calm and meek, ſuitable to the Temper of its <hi>Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thor;</hi>
               <pb n="37" facs="tcp:64677:27"/>no Heats of Paſſion in it, no vehement Outcries or Exaggerati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons; nothing to raiſe thoſe wild Spirits in men, which make 'em rave, and foam, and toſs about, as if they were poſſeſſed. Not that Length of Prayers is blameworthy in it ſelf, nor yet Vehemence of Action or Speech, which in a <hi>ſober ſenſe</hi> is commendable in Prayer, up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on ſome occaſions; but to ſhew, That Fervour of Devotion is no ways inconſiſtent with <hi>cool blood,</hi> or <hi>fewneſs of words;</hi> and that God is as often at leaſt in the <hi>ſtill ſmall voice,</hi> as in the <hi>earthquake</hi> or <hi>fire.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="13">13. It is a great part of Piety to beſtow due portions of time upon God's Service:
<note place="margin">Mark 14.49.</note> And we find our Saviour therefore often in the Tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple and the Synagogues of the <hi>Jews,</hi> worſhipping God in Publick, as well as frequently retiring <hi>with his Diſciples,</hi> and <hi>by himſelf,</hi>
               <note place="margin">John 18.20. Mark 1.35.</note> to his pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vate Devotions: Though all this
<pb n="38" facs="tcp:64677:28"/>while our Saviour was no ſuch Eu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chite, as to think the greateſt part of his Life ought to be ſpent in Prayer; but he beſtows conſidera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble portions of his time upon his own Refreſhment,
<note place="margin">John 2.1. Luke 22.39.</note> and upon the offices of Humanity and Friend<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip; beſides, what muſt be ſuppo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed to take up the main bulk of his Life, his Working (as it is thought) till Thirty years of Age, at his Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther's Trade: And neither there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore is he for that way of practice which prevailed ſo much in after-Ages, of peoples retiring from the world, and mewing themſelves up in Cells and Cloiſters, that they might have nothing elſe to do, but to Meditate, and Worſhip God: The <hi>Romaniſts</hi> look upon this as the greateſt Perfection in Religion: And what was begun therefore in Primitive Times out of <hi>Neceſſity,</hi> when men were forced to fly into Deſarts to avoid Perſecution, theſe take upon themſelves of <hi>Choice;</hi>
               <pb n="39" facs="tcp:64677:28"/>ſome few, according to the <hi>Original Pattern,</hi> but multitudes in a <hi>fond Imitatiod,</hi> entring themſelves into Monaſteries too often as a cloak of Idleneſs, to ſerve their Bellies and their Luſts, more than God. It is a Remarkable <hi>Saying</hi> of an Ancient Father to ſuch people; <hi>Thou ſepa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rateſt thy ſelf from the World, that no body may ſee thee; but whom doſt thou benefit by this? Hadſt thou been what thou art, thinkeſt thou, if eve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry one had done as thou doſt?</hi> And our Saviour plainly leads the way to the <hi>Father</hi> in this; he is not for ſuch Perfection in Religion as de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtroys one main end of it, which is to make men helpful and beneficial to one another; but he divides the Law into <hi>Two great Commandments,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Mat. 22.38, 39.</note> the Love of God, and of our Neigh bour, which he makes alike neceſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſary to be obſerved, and ſo is not for having one of theſe to ſwallow up the Duties of the other: Tho if <hi>one</hi> muſt neceſſarily be omitted
<pb n="40" facs="tcp:64677:29"/>at any time,
<note place="margin">Mat. 12.7.</note> he is even for preferring Works of <hi>Mercy</hi> and Goodneſs be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore <hi>Sacrifice.</hi> For his own part, the great buſineſs of his Life was, <hi>To go about,
<note place="margin">Acts 10.38.</note> doing good;</hi> not to ſit Muſing continually by himſelf; by which he brought no leſs Glory to God, than Benefit to Mankind. Nor does our Saviour preſcribe any ſet Rules, what time muſt of ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſity be employed upon Acts of Devotion, but leaves this to every man's Conſcience to proportion the time according to his leiſure and op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>portunities. To be ſure, to begin and end the day with God, is the leaſt he requires from us, as being that which Natural Religion teaches to be neceſſary: And yet, would ſome men make a Conſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence of this, tho they work <hi>ſix days in the week,</hi> according to God's gracious Allowance, I queſtion not but they ſerve God as acceptably, in profiting the world by their lawful <hi>Callings,</hi> as the ſevereſt <hi>Recluſe</hi> in
<pb n="41" facs="tcp:64677:29"/>bending his knees continually be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore God.</p>
            <p n="14">14. Repentance is a Duty ſo near a-kin to Piety, that I know no place more proper to ſpeak of it than this. This is a Duty of a ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry ſolemn and ſevere nature, and ſuch as habitual ſinners muſt expect much trouble and contention with themſelves about, before they bring it to perfection: Tho certainly ſuch have little reaſon to complain of any hardſhips in this Duty, as having brought them upon themſelves by their own Fault; and they have much more ground to admire God's Goodneſs in allowing <hi>any place at all</hi> to Repentance, than to charge his Juſtice with Severity in making the Terms of our Reconciliation ſo difficult, were they much more grievous to us, than really they are. For indeed, as the caſe now ſtands, there is nothing in this Duty but what <hi>we our ſelves</hi> ſhould count rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſonable,
<pb n="42" facs="tcp:64677:30"/>were it payable to any of us. To be heartily ſorry for a fault; Who is there that admits a groſs Offender to Mercy without this? Who likewiſe that reckons ſuch a one worthy of new favour, with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out actual ſigns, as well as promiſes of amendment? Though here I ſee no neceſſity for thoſe <hi>heights</hi> of Sorrow which ſome inſiſt upon ſo much, as the only true marks of ſincerity in this Duty; and which, by unwary Applications, have run ſo many into Melancholly, Madneſs, and Deſpair: I am ſure there is very little ground for it in our Savi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>our's Diſcourſes about Repentance: His deſign is rather to <hi>mend,</hi> than to <hi>break</hi> peoples hearts by this Duty; whence we may obſerve,
<note place="margin">Luke 19.8.</note> 
               <hi>Zacheus</hi>'s Repentance is deſcribed by an act of <hi>Reſtitution</hi> alone; and St. <hi>Mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thew</hi>'s by <hi>following</hi> Chriſt,
<note place="margin">Luke 5.28, 29.</note> and enter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taining him at a Feaſt preſently; and the Theif's upon the Croſs,
<note place="margin">Luke 23.41, 42.</note> by humble Confeſſion of his Guilt,
<pb n="43" facs="tcp:64677:30"/>and Faith in the Merits of our Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viour; and not one word all the while of any exceſſive ſorrow that our Saviour preſcribes, in his Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hortations to theſe or any other per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons. It's true, the Prophets often endeavour to awaken the <hi>Jews</hi> from their Spiritual Security, by calling upon them to <hi>Howl,</hi> and <hi>Cry aloud,</hi> and <hi>Rent their hearts,</hi> with like terms of rouzing Rhetorick, a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>greeable to the Genius of the Old Law, which was delivered at firſt in <hi>Thunder</hi> and <hi>Tempeſt.</hi> But ſuch who ſtudy to imitate the Prophets Stile, rather than Chriſt's, I think, ſcarce conſider aright, <hi>What ſpirit they are of:</hi> For ſure our Saviour had hardened ſinners enough to deal with, to provoke him to this Stile, had it been ſuitable to his Temper: Though ſtill it muſt be allowed, there is much of the Hy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perbole in thoſe Expreſſions of the Prophets, (no unuſual Figure a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mong them). And after all, they
<pb n="44" facs="tcp:64677:31"/>themſelves confeſs, That it is not ſo much the <hi>afflicting the ſoul, as turning from wickedneſs,
<note place="margin">Iſa. 58.5.</note> and doing that which is lawful and right,</hi> that God calls Repentance. Not that <hi>Godly Sorrow</hi> is otherwiſe than com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mendable in every degree of it, as it is a ſure ſign of Grace and an ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cellent means of Converſion; it being half way towards Amend<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of any Fault, to be thorough<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly poſſeſſed with trouble and grief for it: And happy therefore is he, whoſe heart being tender, and his Soul touched with a deep ſenſe of his Folly and Ingratitude in offend<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing God, can with <hi>David</hi> and St. <hi>Peter,</hi> melt into Tears preſently at the remembrance of his paſt crimes. But that which is lauda<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble or uſeful, is not always neceſſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry; and I think there is as little reaſon to ſuppoſe it ſhould be ſo in this, as in any other caſe; for there are many Natural circumſtances of Age, Sex, and Conſtitution of bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy,
<pb n="45" facs="tcp:64677:31"/>that cauſe great difference in peoples Inclinations to Sorrow; as, the weaker and more tender they are, the more eaſily they are, gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rally, wrought upon by this Paſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on; Childhood and Old Age are more ſubject to it than Manhood; Women more than Men; ſoft and gentle Natures, more than rough and manlier diſpoſitions: But ſure Salvation does not depend upon ſuch Circumſtances as theſe, which people can no ways help: And if ſome therefore, who upon the moſt ſenſible afflictions are not able to ſhed a Tear, (as there be many of this Temper), ſhall with <hi>Dry Eyes</hi> confeſs their ſins before God, this certainly ſhall never be reckon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed as a Bar to their Acceptance with him.</p>
            <p>This was our Saviour's Life and Doctrine in reſpect of Piety towards God.</p>
            <pb n="46" facs="tcp:64677:32"/>
            <p n="15">15. Look upon our Saviour's Life in reſpect of Duties relating to our ſelves, and it is altogether <hi>of a piece</hi> with what has hitherto been obſerved: His Conduct here does more eſpecially ſhew us the free and generous Temper of his Religion; that the Deſign of it is not to <hi>en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſlave,</hi> but to <hi>enoble</hi> the Spirits of men. The regulating our paſſions aright, is one main Branch of theſe; and as to this, our Saviour was un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>doubtedly the greateſt <hi>Maſter</hi> of his Paſſions, that ever the world knew; for what others boaſted ſo much of only in <hi>Words,</hi> he practiſed in <hi>Deed;</hi> nor were there any Trials therefore ſo <hi>ſevere,</hi> as to alter the Evenneſs of his Mind. When a <hi>Cato</hi> and a <hi>Brutus,</hi> after all their pretences to Philoſophy, fell into the utmoſt de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>grees of impatience at laſt, reviling Providence as weak and unſtable, for not Crowning them with Suc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſs anſwerable to their Virtue; our Saviour could behold his great<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eſt
<pb n="47" facs="tcp:64677:32"/>Merits rewarded with the fouleſt Ingratitude that the world's Malice could invent, and yet <hi>like a lamb be led to the ſlaughter, and not open his mouth</hi> all the while; than which there is certainly no truer evidence of <hi>Greatneſs of Soul,</hi> in ſuch caſes as this, where to murmur is but to reproach Providence, or at beſt to exerciſe our ſpleen to no purpoſe: Though neither does our Saviour ſhew himſelf an example of ſuch <hi>ſenſeleſs unconcern</hi> under any trou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble as is <hi>contrary</hi> to nature. He is not for thoſe <hi>Stoical</hi> Rants of look<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing upon Sickneſs, and Death, and the like bodily Evils, as <hi>things with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out,</hi> that belonged nothing to him; but where things were really bur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thenſome to Nature, he is not aſha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med to expreſs tokens of humane weakneſs, in grieving at them; when the Day of his Sufferings therefore drew nigh, he falls into cruel <hi>Agonies</hi> and Convulſions at the thoughts of thoſe Miſeries he
<pb n="48" facs="tcp:64677:33"/>was to endure; and he gives not up the Ghoſt afterwards, without twice <hi>crying out with a loud voice,
<note place="margin">Mat. 27.46, 50.</note> My God, my God, why haſt thou forſaken me?</hi> The extremity of his Tor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments wringing from him this Complaint; and <hi>that</hi> without any imputation of undutifulneſs to God; there being a great difference betwixt Expoſtulating thus with God in humble ways for ſeeming to forſake us in our troubles, and char<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ging his Providence fooliſhly for ſo doing; nor does our Saviour think it any leſſening to himſelf, or injury to God, to exerciſe his Paſſions up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on much ſlighter occaſions than this; particularly in the caſe of <hi>La<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zarus</hi>'s death,
<note place="margin">Joh. 1.33.</note> where he is ſaid to <hi>weep,</hi> and <hi>groan,</hi> and <hi>be troubled in mind,</hi> whilſt he ſaw the two ſiſters, <hi>Martha</hi> and <hi>Mary,</hi> lamenting over their dead Brother: He was ſenſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble how great an Affliction the loſs of ſo <hi>Dear</hi> a Brother muſt be; and therefore inſtead of Reproving
<pb n="49" facs="tcp:64677:33"/>the <hi>Women</hi> for ſuch natural expreſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſions of love, he diſdains not to ſhew a like tenderneſs of affection <hi>himſelf,</hi> in condoling with them. And indeed, in ſuch caſes as this, Paſſions are not only very innocent, but very uſeful and commendable many times, if reſtrained within due bounds, being only a more Em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phatical way of expreſſing thoſe inward Sentiments of our Souls <hi>by Actions,</hi> which might well become us otherwiſe to do <hi>in Words;</hi> and being deſigned beſides as a <hi>Relief</hi> to Nature, to ſoften thoſe Afflictions by giving them vent, which are apt to ſwell and rage the more in us, by endeavouring to ſtifle them: And when we ſpeak therefore of nothing altering the <hi>Evenneſs</hi> of our Saviour's mind, we ſpeak in a ſenſe anſwerable to the Conſtituti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of Human Nature; not that outward Accidents wrought no change in his Paſſions (for then he muſt have ceaſed to be a Man),
<pb n="50" facs="tcp:64677:34"/>but that they cauſed no ſuch diſtur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bance in him, as was offenſive to Religion, or deſtructive of his own Happineſs and Content. In ſhort, he uſed his Paſſions as <hi>Servants</hi> on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly to Nature and Virtue, not as <hi>Tyrants</hi> over Reaſon and Senſe; whereby he preſcribed the moſt proper limits to them.</p>
            <p n="16">16. Temperance in Eating and Drinking, is another Duty we owe to our ſelves; and the world cannot deny it to be a reaſonable one, if the deſign of it were only to pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerve our <hi>Bodies</hi> in health: Tho here our Saviour's Example is far from obliging us to a <hi>Rechabite</hi> Strictneſs, or to weigh our Meat by Grains and Scruples. <hi>He</hi> that made the World, knew better for what end the Creatures were ſent, than that they ſhould lye upon the ground and periſh: And he had rather therefore undergo the names of <hi>Wine-bibber</hi> and <hi>Glutton,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Mat. 11.19.</note> from
<pb n="51" facs="tcp:64677:34"/>the <hi>Phariſees,</hi> than abridge Man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kind of a due Liberty about theſe things. We may well imagine the occaſion of thoſe baſe Reflections being caſt upon <hi>Chriſt,</hi> was the over preciſeneſs of the <hi>Phariſees</hi> in their Rules of Temperance, who it ſeems would ſtrain at every <hi>Gnat</hi> they met with in their Glaſs or Diſh, though they could ſwallow whole <hi>Camels</hi> laden with Oppreſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing Sins: But our Saviour was not to take his Standard of <hi>Morality</hi> from <hi>their</hi> ſtingy Meaſures; and without any thing of Reſervedneſs therefore, we find him frequenting Plentiful Tables, and Friendly Meetings:
<note place="margin">Mat. 11.19.</note> 
               <hi>The Son of man came eating and drinking,</hi> as he himſelf teſtifies.
<note place="margin">Luke 5.29.</note> He accepts of a <hi>great Feaſt</hi> from his Diſciple <hi>Levi,</hi> as a Conſecration-Entertainment upon his Admiſſion into the Apoſtleſhip. And he fears not to make the <hi>Phari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſees</hi> Witneſſes of his Innocent Free<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>doms at their <hi>own</hi> Tables,
<note place="margin">Luke 11.37.</note> though
<pb n="52" facs="tcp:64677:35"/>he knew how apt they were to vio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>late the Laws of Hoſpitality, in baſely Cenſuring him when he was gone. He appears at the <hi>Marriage-Feaſt of Cana in Galilee,</hi> and ſcru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ples not to work his <hi>firſt</hi> Miracle for ſupplying the Gueſts with Wine, after they had <hi>well drank,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Joh. 2.10.</note> it is ſaid: Not to encourage any thereby in <hi>Beaſtly Exceſs,</hi> but to preſerve the Maſter of the Feaſt, who was his Friend, from Reproach, and to ſhew his Approbation of a <hi>mode<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rate</hi> Chearfulneſs upon ſuch occa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſions; if any <hi>diſordered</hi> themſelves afterwards, (as we find not they did) it was their own fault: Chriſt is no more to be blamed for this, than God Almighty, who provides plentifully for us of all ſorts, tho he knows many are like to make a very bad uſe of his Bounty: Nor can <hi>Any</hi> therefore well deſire great<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er <hi>Liberty</hi> than Chriſt allows here; if they do, I am confident it is not in a ſober fit; for there is nothing
<pb n="53" facs="tcp:64677:35"/>more true, than that if Intempe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rance were impoſed upon men as a Duty, it would be reckoned one of the greateſt Slaveries in the World.</p>
            <p n="17">17. Chaſtity may be reckoned another Duty relating to our ſelves: And this is a Virtue of ſo nice and tender a nature, that the leaſt <hi>im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pure thought</hi> is apt to ſully and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>face it: Though we have little rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon to complain of the Strictneſs of Religion, in reſtraining our <hi>thoughts</hi> about this, if we conſider the proneneſs of our Natures to luſt, how apt they are to take fire at the leaſt ſpark, and to riſe into a flame preſently, if never ſo little encou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>raged. It was neceſſary ſuch Appe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tites ſhould be ſtrongly rooted in mens minds, for the propagation of mankind; ſince it is ſcarce to be thought otherwiſe, that any would undergo the Pain and Trou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble of bringing forth Children and
<pb n="54" facs="tcp:64677:36"/>providing for them, were they not led to it by ſome very <hi>inviting</hi> ſenſe of Pleaſure: But then it was as ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſary for that end, to prevent <hi>Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fuſed Mixtures:</hi> And man there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore is not more poſſeſſed, by the Conſtitution of his Nature, with Deſires towards the Act of Gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration, than with Deteſtation of the Abuſe of it; witneſs thoſe <hi>Sons of Pleaſure,</hi> who indeed are well enough content to injure their Neighbours this way; yet reckon nothing ſo intolerable, as to have the Chaſtity of their Wives or Daughters defiled, or to be called the <hi>Off-ſpring</hi> of ſo baſe an Act. Wherefore to prevent ſo dangerous and odious a Vice, Chriſt endea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vours to deſtroy it at the root, if poſſible, by condemning all un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chaſte Thoughts and Deſires: And to this purpoſe he tells us, That but to <hi>look upon a woman,
<note place="margin">Mat. 5.28.</note> ſo as to luſt after her, is to commit Adultery with her:</hi> It is not to be thought
<pb n="55" facs="tcp:64677:36"/>here, that every firſt Motion of our Hearts towards Laſciviouſneſs, if timely ſuppreſſed, is what our Saviour means by <hi>looking upon a woman;</hi> ſuch imperfect acts as theſe, being declared by the beſt Caſuiſts, to be ſo far from ſins <hi>deſtructive</hi> to Salvation, that they become rather the Parents of Virtue to us, by ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>erciſing our Faith and Obedience. And indeed, were ſuch an act e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nough to conſtitute the <hi>Adultery of the Eye,</hi> the <hi>Phariſees</hi> Practice (as odd as it was) might ſeem no leſs than neceſſary; ſome of whom we are told were wont to walk conti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nually with their eyes ſhut, blun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dering againſt every one they met, only to avoid the ſight of Women. But in ſhort, it is only the <hi>fixing</hi> our Eyes and Imaginations upon one another with wanton Deſires, that our Saviour condemns in this place. And this is ſo far from being a ſla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viſh Impoſition upon us, that it ſerves only to free our minds from
<pb n="56" facs="tcp:64677:37"/>one of the moſt Tyrannous Maſters we can poſſibly be ſubject to; ſuch is the Paſſion of Luſt when once it gets a Head; a paſſion no leſs <hi>vain</hi> than <hi>inſolent,</hi> for the moſt part, as it buſies it ſelf, and torments men with longing after thoſe Objects, which it has no hopes or poſſibi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lity many times of ever enjoying.</p>
            <p n="18">18. The moderating our Affe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctions towards Earthly things, is another Duty owing to our ſelves, that our Saviour very much inſiſts upon; and the more, becauſe the <hi>Phariſees</hi> made ſo light of it;
<note place="margin">Luke 16.14.</note> for the <hi>Phariſees</hi> were <hi>Covetous,</hi> we are told; and ſo little ſenſible were they of any Hurt being in this, that they could <hi>Laugh at Chriſt,</hi> when he talked to them of the impoſſibility of <hi>ſerving God and Mammon</hi> at the ſame time. But our Saviour ſaw enough of this ſin in the <hi>Phariſees,</hi> to convince him of the pernicious effects of it to Religion, and the
<pb n="57" facs="tcp:64677:37"/>Good of Mankind. And had he not ſeen it there, he could as eaſily have foreſeen it in his Diſciple <hi>Ju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>das,</hi> to whoſe <hi>Covetous</hi> Diſpoſition he knew the Loſs of his Precious Blood ſhould be owing: Certainly the greateſt Brand of Infamy that can poſſibly lye upon any one ſin! And well therefore might our Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viour caution his Diſciples againſt this ſin,
<note place="margin">Luke 12.15.</note> with a <hi>Beware of covetouſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs, for the life of man conſiſteth not in the abundance of things which he poſſeſſeth.</hi> The <hi>Heathen</hi> Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>raliſts ſpent much time in expoſing this Vice; and the very ſhame of ſetting their hearts upon things which had ſo little of ſolid Enjoy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men in them, and which were ſo ſoon to have an end, was reckoned argument ſufficient among theſe, for moderating the Affections of every wiſe man towards them: But our Saviour does certainly much improve the Argument, when to the <hi>Frailty</hi> and <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nſatisfactorineſs</hi>
               <pb n="58" facs="tcp:64677:38"/>of Earthly things, he adds the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſideration of a <hi>Glorious Immortality Above,</hi> as a Subject much more fit to employ a Chriſtian's thoughts and care: And ſince our <hi>Treaſure is in Heaven,</hi> well therefore may he require, that our hearts ſhould chiefly there be fixed; that we ſhould <hi>not lay up for our ſelves trea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſures upon earth,
<note place="margin">Mat. 6.20.</note> but lay up treaſures for our ſelves in heaven, where nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther moth nor ruſt do corrupt, nor thieves break through and ſteal.</hi> Our Saviour does not hinder us by this, from providing decent and comfor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>table Maintenance for our ſelves and Relations; for even he himſelf is obſerved to have carried a <hi>Bag</hi> in his Company,
<note place="margin">John 13.29.</note> though his Power of working Miracles, which of it ſelf was ſufficient to feed <hi>Multi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tudes,</hi> ſeemed to give little occaſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on for ſuch a trouble: Nor yet does he require us hereby ſo to with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>draw our Affections from the things of this life, as not to rejoice
<pb n="59" facs="tcp:64677:38"/>or take pleaſure in them; for this is natural, for men to delight in thoſe things which tend to their Eaſe or Benefit; and God would never cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tainly have implanted in us ſuch <hi>ſtrong</hi> Deſires as he has, toward Worldly Happineſs, did he not al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>low us to gratifie them in ſome con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiderable meaſures: But indeed all that our Saviour requires of us a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bout earthly things, is only that we love them not, nor purſue them with that <hi>Greedineſs</hi> and <hi>An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>xiety,</hi> as if we reckoned them our <hi>great End</hi> and <hi>Hope:</hi> And certain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, he that has any ſenſe of a Fu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture State, muſt confeſs this no o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>therwiſe than highly reaſonable, if he conſider what numerous <hi>Temptations and Snares</hi> thoſe that <hi>will be Rich</hi> do fall into; and conſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quently, of what mighty prejudice an over-eager Thirſt after Honour or Wealth is to means Salvation.</p>
            <pb n="60" facs="tcp:64677:39"/>
            <p n="19">19. It may ſeem a very hard Saying of our Saviour's about Rich men,
<note place="margin">Mat. 19.24.</note> That <hi>it is eaſier for a camel to go through the eye of a needle, than for ſuch to enter into the kingdom of God.</hi> But I ſee no neceſſity why any Wealthy perſon now-a-days ſhould think the worſe of his con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dition upon that account: For (beſides that our Saviour does very much ſoften this expreſſion in ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther place, by ſaying only, That a <hi>rich man ſhall hardly enter into the kingdom of heaven);</hi>
               <note place="margin">Mark 10.23.</note> I ſuppoſe the <hi>Kingdom</hi> there ſpoken of, is not the Kingdom of <hi>Glory,</hi> but of <hi>Grace,</hi> as the <hi>Kingdom of God</hi> is often taken in Scripture; and that the place is to be underſtood in reference chiefly to our <hi>Saviour's Times,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Mat. 19.21.</note> as the occa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion of the words does plainly inti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mate: And then, conſidering the neceſſity there was in the firſt Ages of the Church, of mens forſaking <hi>All</hi> many times to follow <hi>Chriſt,</hi> to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gether with the ſcorn that rich men
<pb n="61" facs="tcp:64677:39"/>expoſed themſelves to by taking ſo outwardly-mean a Profeſſion upon themſelves, it is little to be won<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dred at, if <hi>ſuch</hi> were very hardly brought to ſubject themſelves to the Goſpel upon theſe terms: But theſe reaſons being ceaſed now in a great meaſure, the conſequences of them muſt be ſuppoſed to be ceaſed too; and as to Riches in them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves, they are certainly of great advantage to Religion; and our Saviour therefore has left ſeveral marks of his Honourable Eſteem of them:
<note place="margin">Mat. 2.11.</note> Three of the earlieſt Wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhippers therefore that he had, are reckoned Perſons of a Princely Rank, from whom our Saviour re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceived Royal Preſents, as the Firſt-Fruits of that Service which <hi>Kings</hi> and <hi>Great Perſons</hi> were to pay him afterwards, when by their Wealth and Authority they were to become <hi>Nurſing Fathers</hi> to his Church: And as this was one of the firſt pieces of Reſpect he accepted upon
<pb n="62" facs="tcp:64677:40"/>earth, ſo the laſt office that was paid to him, was performed by a Rich man: When his Body was to be buried, who ſo fit to be intruſted with thoſe <hi>Sacred Remains</hi> of his, as that <hi>Honourable Counſellor,
<note place="margin">Mat. 27.57.</note> Joſeph of Arimathea?</hi> Nor is it any Obje<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction againſt Wealth, That our Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viour was pleaſed to take a poor condition upon himſelf; for Chriſt had many ends of Religion to ſerve by this, which no one is char<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ged with now-a-days: This ſhew<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, that he ſought not the things of this world, but God's Glory, and the good of mens Souls alone; which muſt advance the Credit of his Doctrine very much: This took off from any Objection that might be made, as if his Miracles were the effects of deep ſearch into the ſecrets of Nature; his Doctrine, of Learning or Study; whence the <hi>Jews,</hi> being confounded at his <hi>Wiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom and Mighty Works,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Mat. 13.55.</note> cried out, <hi>Is not this the Carpenter's ſon?</hi> This,
<pb n="63" facs="tcp:64677:40"/>laſtly, gave his Enemies the more edge and power to perſecute him as they did, and at laſt to bring him to that <hi>Accurſed Slaviſh Death,</hi> the Death upon the Croſs, wherein the Myſtery of our Redemption does not a little conſiſt. In ſhort then, let but men make a right uſe of their Riches, and Chriſt has no Exception againſt them for <hi>being Rich.</hi> Wealth is ſo far then from being a Hindrance to Salvation, that as if the Court of Heaven were capable of being Brib'd, we are adviſed by our Saviour to <hi>make friends to our ſelves</hi> there <hi>of this Mammon of unrighteouſneſs.</hi>
               <note place="margin">Luk. 16.9.</note> Un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>righteous Mammon he calls it; not that it is unrighteous <hi>in it ſelf,</hi> but by reaſon of that unrighte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous uſe that people generally make of it.</p>
            <p n="20">20. One ill effect of Riches, as of all other Acquirements that are wont to raiſe Credit and Eſteem to
<pb n="64" facs="tcp:64677:41"/>us, is, That they are apt to make men Proud and Conceited of their own Abilities; as appears more eſpecially in the <hi>Phariſees,</hi> who were certainly <hi>the vaineſt of men,</hi> what on account of their Tempo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ral, what of their Spiritual En<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dowments; for they loved <hi>greet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ings in the market places,
<note place="margin">Mat. 23.5, 6, 7.</note> and the up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>permoſt ſeats in the ſynagogues;</hi> as our Saviour obſerves of them; they affected to walk in <hi>long robes, and make broad their Philacteries;</hi> and delighted hugely in being call'd <hi>Rabbi,</hi> or great Doctor, at every word. And our Saviour does not only reflect upon the <hi>Phariſees</hi> of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten for this, but in oppoſition to it preſcribes <hi>Humbleneſs</hi> of Mind as a Temper highly neceſſary to ſuch who would be called his Diſciples; propoſing himſelf more particular<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, as a Pattern of this Virtue: <hi>Learn of me,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Mat. 11.29.</note> ſays he, <hi>for I am meek and lowly in heart;</hi> and for an En<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>couragement to it, telling us, That
<pb n="65" facs="tcp:64677:41"/>
               <hi>he that humbleth himſelf ſhall be exalted.</hi> The <hi>Heathen Ethicks</hi> were very defective in Precepts of this nature; as no wonder it ſhould be ſo, among ſuch who made World<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly Glory and Applauſe the great <hi>End</hi> of their Actions: And I think it muſt be allowed, nothing more vain can be imagined, than a paſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſage we meet with to this purpoſe in <hi>Pliny the Younger;</hi> a man other<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe of great Wiſdom and Mode<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſty: He tells us a Story in one of his Epiſtles, of a <hi>ſtranger</hi> talking accidentally with <hi>Tacitus;</hi> and wondring at the Learning and Judgment of the man, he deſired to know <hi>who he was;</hi> ſays <hi>Tacitus, You know me, and that by my Wri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tings. What then,</hi> replied the Gen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tleman, <hi>are you</hi> Pliny, <hi>or</hi> Tacitus? <hi>It is not to be expreſſed,</hi> ſays <hi>Pliny,</hi> reflecting upon this Paſſage, <hi>what pleaſure I took in hearing my Name brought in thus; as if</hi> Tacitus <hi>and</hi> Pliny <hi>were Proper Names, not of
<pb n="66" facs="tcp:64677:42"/>Men, but of Learning.</hi> Upon which he adds another Story of himſelf, no leſs fulſome; That ſitting at Table one day with a Friend of his, where there was alſo a <hi>Countrey Gentleman</hi> preſent; ſays his Friend to the Gentleman, <hi>That's Pliny;</hi> pointing at him, and running pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſently into high Commendations of his Parts: <hi>I muſt needs confeſs,</hi> ſays <hi>Pliny</hi> here, <hi>that I receive much fruit of my Labours from this.</hi> And then he proceeds to vindicate this fond humour, from a parallel caſe of <hi>Demoſthenes,</hi> who it ſeems was not a little pleaſed to ſee an <hi>Old Wo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man</hi> pointing out at him, and cry<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, <hi>That's Demoſthenes.</hi> A man would wonder ſuch Vanity as this ſhould enter the thoughts of any wiſe man, as being ſo unſeemly a humour, that (whatever people may have of it in their hearts), moſt are aſhamed to <hi>own</hi> it even to their moſt Boſom-Friends: Tho I confeſs it is no eaſie matter to fix
<pb n="67" facs="tcp:64677:42"/>bounds to our Duty in this particu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lar, (however nauſeous ſuch ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>travagant Vainglory, as that I have mentioned, muſt appear): It being very unnatural to ſuppoſe a man of real worth can be otherwiſe than <hi>ſenſible</hi> of it himſelf; and it being no leſs ſo, to think that ſuch a one ſhould not receive <hi>ſome</hi> ſatisfaction from the praiſe and good opinion of the world: Beſides that one great Encouragement is loſt to Vir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tue by this: And our Saviour therefore preſſes Humility it ſelf, in the caſe of <hi>not taking the upper, but rather the lowermoſt ſeat at feaſts,</hi> under this conſideration, That we ſhall have <hi>worſhip of men</hi> for ſo doing.
<note place="margin">Luke 14.10.</note> But then, the leſs men have of Pride or Vainglory in their hearts, the more it's certain they have of Chriſt's Temper; and there is very little danger, to be ſure, from the contrary extreme: And ſtill Religion will teach us, That to Pride our ſelves in any Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cellency,
<pb n="68" facs="tcp:64677:43"/>is to Pride our ſelves in Feathers that are not our own, ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving nothing but what we <hi>receive</hi> from God; and that to aſſume the glory of ſuch things to our ſelves, is to derogate <hi>ſo much</hi> from God's Honour, to whom <hi>every good and perfect gift</hi> ought to be aſcribed, with all ſubmiſſion and acknow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledgment of our dependency on him; accordingly as our Saviour tells us of himſelf, That in all things he ſought <hi>not his own,
<note place="margin">John 8.50.</note> but his Father's glory.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>This was our Saviour's Life and Doctrine in reſpect of Duties re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lating to our ſelves.</p>
            <p n="21">21. Conſider our Saviour's Life in reſpect of Duties relating to our Neighbour, and you will find no part of Religion that he lays great<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er <hi>ſtreſs</hi> upon; however ſome are pleaſed to vilifie the Duties of it under the Notion of <hi>Heathen Vir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tues:</hi> Nor did any thing therefore
<pb n="69" facs="tcp:64677:43"/>render the <hi>Phariſees</hi> the ſubject of his Scorn and Deteſtation more, than their groſs neglects of theſe Duties: Theſe Duties he compre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hends in general under that great Precept of <hi>Loving our neighbour as our ſelves:</hi>
               <note place="margin">John 13.34.</note> A Precept that he ſeems more than ordinary fond of; and therefore he calls it a <hi>New Command</hi> in one place; and in another, he hids us take notice, that it was <hi>His Command;</hi>
               <note place="margin">John 15.12.</note> as if he were jealous leſt any one ſhould rob him of the Honour of being a principal Patron and Founder of it. And to ſhew his Eſteem of it yet farther, he pitches upon this, before all other Duties of Religion,
<note place="margin">John 13.35.</note> as a Mark whereby his Diſciples ought to <hi>di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtinguiſh</hi> themſelves from the reſt of the world: Nor is it to be won<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dred at, that Chriſt laid ſo great ſtreſs upon this Precept, ſince there is nothing that tends more to the Honour and Intereſt of Religion, than a compliance with the ſeveral
<pb n="70" facs="tcp:64677:44"/>Duties of it; theſe being ſuch as are of univerſal applauſe among perſons of all Religions, and ſuch therefore, as muſt mightily recom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mend Chriſtianity to men, when they ſee <hi>that</hi> an effectual Promoter of ſuch things as they moſt eſteem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed; whereas ſhould Chriſtians have neglected theſe, the Scandal would have been ſure to have been impu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted to their Religion, and no man would have embraced that Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrine which ſeemed to confound Nature, and to root out the Prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciples of Mercy and Truth, the great things whereby the Happineſs of this world is maintained. And this I reckon one main reaſon why our Saviour made Love the <hi>Diſtin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guiſhing Badge</hi> of his Diſciples. No queſtion but there are ſeveral Marks of Faith and other Graces, where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by Chriſtians may and ought to be diſtinguiſhed from perſons of other Religions: But this of Love is ſuch a Livery, as appears beautiful
<pb n="71" facs="tcp:64677:44"/>and amiable in every body's eye: And no wonder therefore Chriſt made choice of it, as that which muſt needs redound much to the Credit of its Maſter.</p>
            <p n="22">22. Faithfulneſs in Dealings is one Duty owing to our Neighbour, that is neceſſary above all others for the Peace and Welfare of mankind: And a ſmall matter of Religion, one would think, might be ſuffici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ent to keep men <hi>right</hi> in this, ſince Nature it ſelf abhors a contrary practice: Tho indeed we find none more wanting in this, than thoſe that pretend moſt to Religion. The <hi>Phariſees</hi> Character too fre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quently ſhews it ſelf in ſuch, that they are <hi>graves which appear not;
<note place="margin">Luke 11.44.</note> and thoſe that walk over them are not a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ware of them</hi> However ſcrupu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lous they may be in other points, they can <hi>devour widows houſes</hi> with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out the leaſt remorſe, and boaſt themſelves the Saints of God at the
<pb n="72" facs="tcp:64677:45"/>ſame time; as if they had a parti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cular <hi>Licenſe</hi> from Heaven to de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceive: Certainly a great Diſhonour to Religion this, and ſuch as makes Chriſtianity too often to ſtink in the Noſtrils of Infidels and Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phane perſons; and no queſtion ſo much the worſe, by how much the perſons guilty of it, do make pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſion of greater <hi>Sanctity</hi> in other things. We muſt not expect ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny Inſtances of this Duty of Faith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fulneſs in our Saviour's Life, as being beneath the Excellency of his Character, to have Virtues of <hi>ſo ordinary a ſize</hi> mentioned of him: Tho in general we are told of him, That there was <hi>no guile found in his mouth.</hi>
               <note place="margin">1 Pet. 2.22.</note> And how grateful ſuch a Character was to him, we have one remarkable Inſtance, in that kind <hi>Welcome</hi> he gave to <hi>Nathanael</hi> on account of it, when being preſent<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed to him, he cried out, with no leſs Delight than Admiration,
<note place="margin">Joh. 1.47.</note> 
               <hi>Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hold an Iſraelite indeed, in whom is
<pb n="73" facs="tcp:64677:45"/>no guile.</hi> We muſt not think that by <hi>Guile</hi> here, our Saviour means downright Knavery and Fraud a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lone; but every undermining, over<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reaching act, whereby we impoſe upon the Weakneſs or Ignorance of our Brother; which is plainly im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plied in that <hi>Dovelike Harmleſneſs</hi> he recommends to his Followers:
<note place="margin">Mat. 10.16.</note> And however therefore ſome peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple may value themſelves upon their Craftineſs, it is certainly no great Commendation of this Qua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lity, that our Saviour called <hi>Herod Fox,</hi> as one of the higheſt marks of his Deteſtation of him. Not that our Saviour deſigns hereby to make men weak, and unwary, or Fools in Buſineſs; for <hi>Prudence</hi> and <hi>Simplicity</hi> are well joined toge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther by the <hi>Poet;</hi> and our Saviour therefore commends the <hi>Wiſdom of the Serpent,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Ibid.</note> at the ſame time that he requires the <hi>Harmleſneſs of the Dove:</hi> But when Wiſdom is made uſe of for circumventing people to
<pb n="74" facs="tcp:64677:46"/>their damage, it degenerates into Guile and Craft: And this is ſo a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bominable in Chriſt's eſteem, that I queſtion not but to ſhew, the <hi>Phariſees</hi> themſelves might have eſcaped that odious Cenſure of Hy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pocriſy from him, were it not for <hi>this more eſpecially,</hi> among other Vices of a like nature, that they were Godly Cheats, men that <hi>walk<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed in ſheeps cloathing, but inwardly were ravening wolves.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="23">23. Mercy, or Forgiveneſs of Injuries and Debts, is another Du<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty owing to our Neighbour, which our Saviour preſſes very earneſtly upon his Diſciples: And it may ſeem a ſtrange <hi>unimitable</hi> Pattern he propoſes about this, when he com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mands us to be <hi>merciful,
<note place="margin">Luk 6.36.</note> as our hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venly father is merciful:</hi> Thought indeed there is nothing here, but what human ſtrength, aſſiſted by God's Grace, is well able to per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>form; and nothing, beſides, but
<pb n="75" facs="tcp:64677:46"/>what Nature and Right Reaſon will challenge from us: As to Debts, he that will not forgive theſe <hi>in whole,</hi> when a Debtor is <hi>al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>together</hi> unable to pay; or <hi>in part,</hi> when he has reaſon to think the poor man's Neceſſities very great and pinching, muſt certainly be rec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>koned a very <hi>hard man:</hi> And I be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieve no one can read the Parable of the <hi>unjuſt ſteward taking his poor deb<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tors by the throat,
<note place="margin">Mat. 18.28.</note> and hurrying them away to goal,</hi> without abhorrence of his Cruelty: And yet this is all that God's Example obliges us to, in reſpect of Debts: <hi>He himſelf</hi> forgives not ſuch Debts, but which we are unable to pay; and he re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quires ſubmiſſion here from us, and acknowledgment of his Favour, before the Bonds are cancelled. And it is much the ſame thing in reſpect of Injuries: For are the Injuries of a light nature, ſome ſlips only of weakneſs or inadver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tency? Theſe God paſſes by in us,
<pb n="76" facs="tcp:64677:47"/>without particular Repentances; and it muſt be a very ill temper that will not do as much as this comes to, to his offending Brother. Or are they more heinous and groſs? Here God expects Confeſſion of our Guilt, and hearty Deſires of Forgiveneſs, before our Pardon is <hi>paſſed:</hi> And there is no Generous Soul but will accept a like <hi>Satisfa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction.</hi> If Puniſhment be neceſſary (as it ſometimes is, in ſuch caſes) for correcting the Offender, and for the Warning and Terror of o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers, God's example does war<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rant men in this alſo, provided they puniſh Tranſgreſſors as he does, out of hatred to their Crimes, and not to their Perſons: So that to imitate God's Mercy, is no other than a Duty highly reaſonable and natural to men: And as there is no greater meaſure of Perfection than this, ſo we may well think Chriſt requires no more from us. Upon theſe terms, the <hi>Forgiving</hi> ſo often
<pb n="77" facs="tcp:64677:47"/>in a day, as Chriſt commands, even <hi>ſeventy times ſeven,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Mat. 18.22.</note> is no hard Du<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty; for by <hi>Forgiveneſs</hi> there, I can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not think Chriſt means an abſolute paſſing by of Faults, though never ſo little; the leaſt faults, when ſo often repeated, being juſtly inter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preted of Obſtinacy and groſs Ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>glect, which are Crimes that high<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly deſerve Puniſhment; and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore <hi>to forgive</hi> there, is only not to bear malice or ill will againſt a man; in which ſenſe we may for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>give, though we correct at the ſame time. Nor is it any thing of an unreaſonable impoſition, that we are commanded to imitate God, in <hi>loving</hi> and <hi>doing good</hi> to thoſe that injure us:
<note place="margin">Mat. 5.44.</note> For God himſelf is not wont to take his Enemies into his boſom, whilſt they continue ſuch, but only to afford them the ordinary Bleſſings of his Provi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence: And what Man of Honour will carry his Reſentments ſo far, as to deny an Enemy the common
<pb n="78" facs="tcp:64677:48"/>offices of humanity and pity, in time of Want? Who is not ſenſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble of the Glory of ſuch Acts, when men are kind and helpful to thoſe that deſerve <hi>worſt</hi> of them?</p>
            <p n="24">24. But there is no part of this Duty of Forgiveneſs that fleſh and blood riſes ſo much againſt, as that of <hi>turning the other cheek:</hi>
               <note place="margin">Mat. 5.39.</note> Nor in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deed is there any thing more con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tradictory to Reaſon, as well as to the Spirit of a man, than to bear injuries at this rate. Thoſe muſt be very ſervile creatures that will ſtoop down thus to take their bur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dens; and even <hi>Worms</hi> therefore are taken notice of to turn again when they are trampled upon. Wherefore neither did our Saviour himſelf obſerve this Command in a literal ſenſe; for when he was ſmitten by a <hi>Servant</hi> before the <hi>High Prieſt,</hi>
               <note place="margin">John 18.22.</note> we find not that he turned the other Cheek preſently, but he expoſtulates with the perſon
<pb n="79" facs="tcp:64677:48"/>that did the Injury, and that not without ſome marks of <hi>concern</hi> at the Injuſtice done him: And gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rally therefore this Precept is rec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>koned to relate to <hi>leſſer</hi> Injuries and Affronts, which our Saviour would have men to <hi>put up,</hi> rather than by drawing the Saw of Contention to widen the Breach into downright <hi>fallings out;</hi> or to give greater trou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble to our ſelves and others, in Law-Suits and exchange of Blows, than the Injury is worth: In which ſenſe this Precept of our Saviour's is no leſs reaſonable than any other part of the Duty of Forgiveneſs. It may ſeem ſtrange indeed to ſome, that the receiving a Blow on the Face ſhould be reckoned here a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mong <hi>leſſer</hi> Injuries, when it is thought by many now-a-days to deſerve little leſs than a <hi>Stab:</hi> But we muſt conſider here, that our Savi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>our ſpoke to perſons of <hi>mean Rank,</hi> among whom Injuries of this na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture are not ſo highly provoking;
<pb n="80" facs="tcp:64677:49"/>though no queſtion the practice of this Age in demanding the <hi>Blood</hi> of each other upon theſe and the like Affronts, (let the <hi>Quality</hi> of the Perſon be what it will) is ſuffici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ently againſt our Saviour's Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mand here: And it is certainly no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing of ſound Reaſon, but vain Cuſtom alone, that makes people ſtand at this high rate upon <hi>Puncti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lio's</hi> of Honour: For how unreaſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nable is it in it ſelf, that nothing leſs than the Death of a man, and in that the ruin of a <hi>whole Family</hi> many times, ſhall ſerve as an Atone<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment for giving me <hi>the Lye,</hi> ſup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe? And what a Madneſs is it in any caſe, becauſe a man has inju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red me, that therefore I will ven<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture my Life with him upon <hi>equal</hi> Terms, in way of making my ſelf Satisfaction? I will confeſs here, that Honour is a great Bleſſing to men, and ſuch therefore as they ought to be very tender of preſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving: And ſince Cuſtom has
<pb n="81" facs="tcp:64677:49"/>brought it to <hi>that,</hi> that a man can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not <hi>tamely</hi> ſit down, and ſuffer ſome kind of Abuſes (no ways heinous in themſelves neither), without expoſing himſelf to Igno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miny and Diſgrace all his life after, it makes the caſe very hard: Some mens Livelihoods, we know, de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pend upon the Reputation of their Courage; and every other perſon has juſt reaſon to keep himſelf from being deſpiſed and trampled upon: But as Cuſtom and Conni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vence have brought thoſe <hi>falſe No<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions</hi> of Honour into Faſhion, up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on which this Murdering Practice is founded; ſo we preſume Autho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity might ſoon baniſh them out of the world, by good Laws, and ſtrict Execution; as has been done in a great meaſure in a Neighbour<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing Kingdom. And till this be done, it is little to be expected that other Arguments ſhould ſignifie much, for rooting ſuch <hi>fond Prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciples</hi> out of mens minds. How<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ever,
<pb n="82" facs="tcp:64677:50"/>true it is, That no greater Scandal can lye upon this Age, than that it ſhould be reckoned the greateſt Reproach in it, to obey a plain Command of <hi>Chriſt</hi>'s; and that nothing can be imagined more <hi>deſperate,</hi> than for men to hazard their lives thus <hi>in the very Breach</hi> of a Command, which (to ſay no worſe) muſt highly endanger their Souls to all Eternity.</p>
            <p n="25">25. Another Duty of Love owing to our Neighbour, is that of Charity, or a being kind and beneficial to perſons in Miſery and Want. In which our Saviour did more eſpecially <hi>ſignalize</hi> himſelf: For it was the great buſineſs of his Life,
<note place="margin">Act. 10.38.</note> we are told, to <hi>go about, do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing good:</hi> And accordingly we find him every where engaged; ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>times as a Phyſician to the Sick, vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiting and curing them of their ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veral Diſtempers; and among theſe, the poorer ſort were gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rally
<pb n="83" facs="tcp:64677:50"/>the objects of his Tenderneſs and Care; the Maimed, the Halt, the Blind, the Leper, ſuch as he found in the ſtreets incapacitated for labour, and ſo begging for a Subſiſtence. Sometimes we find him as a Reliever of mens Neceſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſities in other ways: His Bowels yearned at the Faſting of the Mul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>titude in the Wilderneſs; and ſo, rather than ſend them away empty, he firſt beſtows upon them all the little Proviſions he could get,
<note place="margin">Mat. 15.34.</note> and then <hi>twice</hi> works a Miracle to ſup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ply what was wanting. And it is very obſervable, That almoſt <hi>all</hi> the Miracles our Saviour wrought, had ſome Charitable work for their ſubject; contrary to thoſe of <hi>Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes</hi> and the reſt of the Prophets. It would certainly have ſerved as well for anſwering the chief De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſign of his Miracles, if they had been matter only of Amazement and Aſtoniſhment to the people; for thereby it would have appear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed,
<pb n="84" facs="tcp:64677:51"/>That he was an extraordinary Perſon ſent from God; and this was the main End of his Miracles, to atteſt the Truth and Divinity of his Commiſſion: But this was not e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nough, he thought, unleſs Chari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty alſo was added to them: Our Saviour would have his Wondrous Works receive no leſs Glory from the <hi>Goodneſs,</hi> than the <hi>Strangeneſs</hi> of them: All which we may juſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly think our Saviour did, to ſhew himſelf an Example of <hi>that</hi> which he deſired the moſt of any thing to engage his Followers to the pra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctice of, as being not only a moſt excellent Duty in it ſelf, and moſt agreeable with his own Temper, but ſuch alſo as tends in the higheſt degrees to the Honour and Intereſts of his Religion; for Charity is the moſt beautiful part of a Chriſtians Badge; and there is nothing that attracts the eyes and hearts of men more than <hi>this.</hi> Even the <hi>Jews</hi> themſelves therefore were wrought
<pb n="85" facs="tcp:64677:51"/>by <hi>this</hi> into a good opinion of <hi>Chriſt,</hi> when the Excellency of his Doctrine made little impreſſion up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on their hearts:
<note place="margin">Mar. 7.37.</note> 
               <hi>He hath done all things well,</hi> ſay they; <hi>he maketh the deaf to hear, and the dumb to ſpeak.</hi> The Primitive Chriſtians brought infinite Credit to their Religion by it, when in the time of a great Plague at <hi>Alexandria,</hi> they viſited the Sick, and relieved the poor, and buried the Dead, <hi>even</hi> of their Heathen Adverſaries, when their <hi>own</hi> Friends would take no care of them. And it would be no leſs Diſcredit to our Faith, were that true which the <hi>Romaniſts</hi> object a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt us, That our Religion is <hi>barren</hi> and <hi>unfruitful</hi> in ſuch good works as theſe: Though I think we may ſafely enough defie them to make good their Charge; when a Reverend <hi>Author</hi> in King <hi>James</hi> the Firſt's time, has given us a par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticular Account of Charities be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtowed upon Colleges, Hoſpitals,
<pb n="86" facs="tcp:64677:52"/>Free-Schools, and the like Pious Uſes, within the compaſs of Sixty Years ſince the Reformation, a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mounting to a Million of Money: That which he challenges <hi>any</hi> Age of Popery to parallel in this King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom. And I think this Age has gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven ſufficient Evidence to ſtop the mouths of our Adverſaries, of the reſpect they bear to this <hi>great Duty</hi> of Religion, in thoſe Liberal Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tributions they have made of late to <hi>Diſtreſſed Strangers,</hi> as well as in every other Inſtance of Chari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty. Which alſo ought the more to be taken notice of, for that it is done in a free generous way, from the voluntary motions and inclina<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions of the Benefactors alone; not <hi>grudgingly, or of neceſſity,</hi> as it frequently happened in former times, when people were frighted into Charity by their Confeſſors, ſorely againſt their wills, only to make compoſition for Pardon of their ſins. <hi>May our light ſtill ſo ſhine
<pb n="87" facs="tcp:64677:52"/>before men, that others ſeeing our good works, may glorifie our Father which is in heaven.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="26">26. There is nothing that tends to the eaſe and benefit of mankind, that ſeems beneath our Saviour's Care: And therefore, beſides theſe <hi>greater</hi> Duties that we owe to our Neighbour, he inſiſts upon others that may ſeem of <hi>leſſer</hi> moment, though they are of no ſmall com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fort to thoſe among whom we con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſe. Such, particularly, is that of not being <hi>Angry with our Brother raſhly, or without a cauſe:</hi> For in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deed there is nothing that deſtroys the Bleſſings of Society more, than this Vice of Anger;
<note place="margin">Prov. 21.19.</note> what <hi>Solomon</hi> ſays of <hi>an angry woman,</hi> being cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tainly as true of <hi>an angry man, It is better to live in a wilderneſs, than where ſuch be.</hi> Beſides, that the Conſequences of this Vice are of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tentimes very miſchievous and fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tal; Anger being a Paſſion of a
<pb n="88" facs="tcp:64677:53"/>very bloody and deſperate nature; whereever it is ſuffered to grow to <hi>a head,</hi> it knows no rules or bounds. The two Sons of <hi>Zebedee</hi> would have deſtroyed a whole City in a mad Fit of this Paſſion, had Chriſt been as ready to furniſh them with Inſtruments of Revenge, as they were to call for them: And we have multitudes of Inſtances in every Age, of peoples murdering their <hi>Deareſt Friends,</hi> and doing other things in their Anger, which have proved Wounds to their Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>putations and their Minds, <hi>never</hi> to be cured in this World: Where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore our Saviour preſſes the Duty of not being Angry, under as great obligations as any other Du<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty of Religion; for he tells us, That no leſs a danger attends the breach of it, than <hi>that</hi> of the Judgment,
<note place="margin">Mat. 5.22.</note> and of Hell-Fire. And to ſhew of how great eſteem it is in God's ſight, he repreſents it as ſuch, without which God will ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cept
<pb n="89" facs="tcp:64677:53"/>no Sacrifice from us;
<note place="margin">— 24.</note> 
               <hi>Leave thy gift at the Altar,</hi> therefore he ſays, <hi>go thy way, firſt be reconciled to thy brother, and then come and offer thy gift.</hi> Not that our Saviour would make his Diſciples hereby ſuch <hi>poor paſſive</hi> creatures, as to hinder them from expreſſing their Reſentments with ſhews of An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger, upon <hi>juſt</hi> occaſions: For by commanding us not to be angry with our Brother <hi>without a cauſe,</hi> he plainly inſinuates, that in ſome ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes a man may have <hi>juſt</hi> cauſe of being angry: And we find there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore that he himſelf looked upon the <hi>Phariſees with anger at the hard<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs of their hearts;</hi>
               <note place="margin">Mark 3.5.</note> and that (by the Privilege of his Prophetick Office) he called <hi>Herod Fox,</hi> in way of Indignation,
<note place="margin">Luke 13.32.</note> when the Meſſage was brought that <hi>Herod</hi> had a <hi>deſign to kill him.</hi> Where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore it is only ſome <hi>Exceſſes</hi> and <hi>Ir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>regularities</hi> of this Paſſion, that our Saviour reproves, when he con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demns
<pb n="90" facs="tcp:64677:54"/>Anger as a Vice: As, when it breaks out upon trivial occaſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons; when it is diſproportioned to its cauſe; when it ſwells to immo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derate heights; when it rankles and breeds bad Blood in us; every of which are things not only ſo miſchievous in their conſequences, but ſo unſeemly in themſelves be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſides, that if Chriſt had not forbid them, our <hi>own Conſciences</hi> would have done it: And there is nothing of a Wiſe or Brave man therefore, but though he may be taken ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>times in ſuch Indecencies, is aſha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med of himſelf afterwards. Whilſt the Blood indeed is up, and the mouth ſwells with big words, a man appears to himſelf very Great, and he Lords it with no ſmall Pride and Tyranny over thoſe who are bound in <hi>Duty</hi> or <hi>Intereſt</hi> not to oppoſe him: But he that ſtands by, and conſiders the poor grounds upon which this <hi>deal a-do</hi> is often made, is ſo far from admiring the
<pb n="91" facs="tcp:64677:54"/>Greatneſs of the man's Soul, that he does but pity his Weakneſs all the while. They are the ſhallow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eſt ſtreams that are generally moſt Noiſy, and moſt ſubject to over<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>flow: And a man therefore that values his Reputation, would keep a ſtrict hand over himſelf about this Paſſion, tho he had no other obligation to reſtrain him.</p>
            <p n="27">27. Cenſoriouſneſs is another Vice oppoſite to the Duties of Love, which may ſeem of <hi>leſſer</hi> moment to our Neighbour's good, though it cauſe none of the leaſt uneaſineſſes to him: This our Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viour frequently reflects upon the <hi>Phariſees</hi> for; who, it may ſeem, reckoned it a greater piece of Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lineſs to Judge <hi>other</hi> peoples Faults, than to Correct their <hi>own:</hi> And all their Diſcourſe therefore ran upon this ſubject; and they could not ſo much as Pray to God, but they muſt tell him of their Neighbours
<pb n="92" facs="tcp:64677:55"/>Faults, and thank him that they were <hi>not as other men,
<note place="margin">Luke 18.11.</note> not as this Publican:</hi> It was much the worſe, to be ſure, that their Cenſoriouſneſs was generally attended with Pride and Uncharitable Aggravations; though it had been bad enough, had it been only a ſupercilious re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>proving their Neighbours conti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nually for leſſer faults, which for the moſt part they had no other ground to condemn, than that they were not according to their own Pedantick ways of walking: For this is what our Saviour means, by their <hi>beholding the mote in their bro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers eye,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Mat. 7.1, 3.</note> which gave occaſion to his Precept of <hi>not judging.</hi> And indeed this muſt render Converſe ſo very uneaſie to men, and conſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quently Religion ſo uncomfortable a thing, when upon every appear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ance of evil they muſt be diſcipli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned and Schooled by their Friends, that it is more to be feared they ſhould be hardned againſt <hi>all</hi> Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>proof,
<pb n="93" facs="tcp:64677:55"/>than to be hoped they ſhould amend by it; which is the greateſt diſ-ſervice we can do either to Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligion or our Neighbour's Soul. No queſtion but to reprove people with Candor and Diſcretion, is an excellent Duty in it ſelf; and there is no office of Love more worthy the name of <hi>true</hi> Friendſhip: But to perform this aright, requires more of Temper and Prudence than the Vulgar are generally Maſters of. And that men may uſe all Caution therefore in it, we find our Saviour more ſolicitous in condemning the oppoſite <hi>Extreme,</hi> than in enfor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cing the <hi>Duty.</hi> Particularly, where Reproof is like to do more harm than good, Chriſt has given us Ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vice very plainly, in a prudential way, not to expoſe Religion and our ſelves in ſuch caſes:
<note place="margin">Mat. 7.6.</note> 
               <hi>Give not that which is holy unto dogs, neither caſt your pearls before ſwine, leſt they trample them under foot, and turn again and rent you.</hi> Though this is
<pb n="94" facs="tcp:64677:56"/>to be underſtood, not without ſome Reſerve to Parents, and Miniſters, and Maſters of Families, and the like, whoſe Duty it is to be <hi>inſtant in ſeaſon and out of ſeaſon,</hi> in repro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving thoſe committed to their Charge; as there is much leſs dan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger of their Reproof being deſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed by ſuch, than by Strangers or Friends; it being the proper buſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs of <hi>their</hi> Office to do this, which few are ſo unreaſonable as not to make ſome allowance for; and more eſpecially, theſe having Authority on their ſide to back their Reproofs with Correction, where the former work not the effect deſigned.</p>
            <p>This as to our Saviour's Life and Doctrine in reſpect of Duties rela<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting to our Neighbour.</p>
            <p n="28">28. I ſhould now put an end to this Diſcourſe, but that I think it convenient to anſwer ſome general Objections that may be brought a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt
<pb n="95" facs="tcp:64677:56"/>it: The principal of which is, The Example of the <hi>Primitive Chriſtians;</hi> whoſe rigid obſervance of many Duties, it muſt be confeſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed, was much beyond the Mea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſures preſcribed here; eſpecially in reſpect of Temperance, Contempt of the World, Mortification, and the like ſelf-denying Virtues. And now in anſwer to this, I muſt de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clare, That I cannot think the <hi>Pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitive Chriſtians</hi> practice an ade<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quate rule of walking to us: For though their Zeal be certainly much to be admired, yet it is plain in ſome things they went as much beyond the bounds of Prudence, as of their Duty: Particularly in the caſe of Martyrdom; a thing they grew ſo fond of in a little time, as to run themſelves <hi>wilfully</hi> into Dangers, and even to <hi>provoke</hi> their Perſecutors to put them to Death: As if our Saviour had gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven no ſuch Advice to his Diſciples,
<note place="margin">Mat. 10.23.</note> to <hi>fly from City to City,</hi> to avoid
<pb n="96" facs="tcp:64677:57"/>Perſecution; and this they did ſometimes in ways ſcarce warranta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble: Such was that of <hi>Apphianus,</hi> a famous Martyr of <hi>Paleſtine,</hi> hold<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the Prefect <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>rbanus</hi>'s hand when he was going to Sacrifice. Inſomuch, that the Church thought fit at laſt in ſeveral Councils to blame this unnatural and overzea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lous Ambition. And neither were their Auſterities leſs ſtrained be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>yond the Limits preſcribed in the Goſpel: <hi>Origen</hi>'s chuſing to lye upon the ground, and walk <hi>bare<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>foot</hi> many years, was more, I am ſure, than any Law of <hi>Chriſt</hi> obli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ged him to; as likewiſe were thoſe ſevere Rules of Temperance, which he and others obſerved in thoſe days: Of which we have a re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>markable Inſtance in one <hi>Alcibiades,</hi> who was wont to live upon Bread and Water for a long time, till it was <hi>Bevealed</hi> (ſays the Hiſtorian) to <hi>Attalus</hi> the Martyr, That the <hi>Man</hi> did not well in refuſing God's
<pb n="97" facs="tcp:64677:57"/>Creatures, and giving offence to his weak brethren: Upon which <hi>Al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cibiades</hi> was prevailed upon to eat and drink as other people, and gave Thanks to God for it. And the ſame muſt be ſaid as to their Renouncing the World, to that degree, many of them, as well nigh to fall under the Apoſtle's Cenſure,
<note place="margin">1 Tim. 5.8.</note> of <hi>not providing for their own;</hi> at leaſt, to come within the compaſs of that <hi>voluntary humility,
<note place="margin">Col. 2.18.</note> and neglecting the body,</hi> which the ſame Apoſtle declares to have only a <hi>ſhew of wiſdom in them.</hi> And it would be endleſs to inſiſt upon e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>very other Duty, wherein the Zeal of thoſe Times was wont to ſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pererogate; as in Watchings and Faſtings, in Vows of Chaſtity, in unmerciful Penances, and the like.</p>
            <p n="29">29. Though here I cannot but admire the Wiſdom of God's Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vidence, in ordering things at this
<pb n="98" facs="tcp:64677:58"/>rate, as well for the good of thoſe that were <hi>already</hi> Converted, as for the Converſion of others in thoſe times: For conſidering what Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſecutions the <hi>Primitive Chriſtians</hi> were to lye under, it was little leſs than neceſſary to infuſe ſuch Prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciples as theſe into their minds: By this means their voluntary Auſte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rities became a ſort of <hi>hardning</hi> to them, to make them fit Soldiers for that ſevere Service they were called to: For it was no great difficulty for ſuch to endure long and cruel Impriſonments, who were wont to lye upon the bare earth, and fare courſly in their or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinary way of life. And this muſt mightily take off from the Pain and Terror of thoſe Tortures which they daily ſaw inflicted upon others, and were at laſt con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demned to themſelves. This made the great <hi>Champions</hi> of the Church, when they mounted the Stage, to be more concerned for their Fel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>low-Sufferers,
<pb n="99" facs="tcp:64677:58"/>leſt through Weak<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs or Tenderneſs of Body, they ſhould be tempted to renounce their Faith (as not being uſed to ſuch <hi>Aſcetick Diſcipline),</hi> than for any miſeries they ſaw prepared for themſelves. Of which we have a notable Inſtance in the caſe of <hi>Blan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dina,</hi> a Martyr of <hi>France;</hi> though by an admirable Fortitude ſhe fru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrated the Fears of her Friends, as well as the Expectation of her E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nemies. And of much greater ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſity was their Contempt of the things of this life, for engaging them to maintain their <hi>Profeſſion</hi> with Reſolution and Conſtancy, amidſt the Perſecutions they lay under. For men that are <hi>Wedded</hi> to the World, are very loth to be <hi>Divor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ced</hi> from it; and there is nothing more difficult, than for <hi>ſuch</hi> to fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>low <hi>Chriſt,</hi> who are faſt tied to Riches, and Honour, and Plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſures. The <hi>Firſt Chriſtians</hi> looked upon theſe things as little better
<pb n="100" facs="tcp:64677:59"/>than the <hi>Incumbrances</hi> of life; and like true <hi>Sojourners</hi> therefore upon Earth, they deſired nothing more, than juſt enough to bear their <hi>Charges</hi> to Heaven. So if Perſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cution ſeized their Eſtates, it was but like robbing them of an <hi>upper Garment,</hi> which they had little need of, and which they were rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy enough to throw off of their own accord; and it could be no doubtful Choice to ſuch, whether they ſhould part with this, or a good Conſcience, which they knew was a Treaſure to them to all E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ternity. If Perſecution reached their Lives alſo, it brought them but the ſooner to their Journey's end, they knew; and they had little reaſon to be otherwiſe than contented with this, who propoſed ſo ſmall a ſhare to themſelves in the Comforts and Enjoyments of this World.</p>
            <pb n="101" facs="tcp:64677:59"/>
            <p n="30">30. Nor do I leſs admire God's Gracious Providence in ordering things at this rate, on account of the <hi>Gentiles</hi> of thoſe times; there being no means more likely than this, for Converting them: For theſe were a ſort of Principles which the <hi>Philoſophy</hi> of that Age ran very much upon; and we no where meet with greater Exam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ples of Severity of Manners, as to Temperance, and Mortification, and Contempt of the World, than the <hi>Schools</hi> of the <hi>Heathens</hi> would at leaſt pretend to in thoſe times. The <hi>Stoicks</hi> were extremely rigid this way, who bid Defiance to all the Comforts of Senſe; and look<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed upon it as a great part of <hi>Wiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom,</hi> to be mean and ſordid in their Habit, pale in their Looks, and poor in their Purſes. The <hi>Plato<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſts,</hi> little inferior to theſe in Strictneſs of Diſcipline, who talked as if they lived <hi>out</hi> of their Bodies, upon Air and Contemplation alone;
<pb n="102" facs="tcp:64677:60"/>Concerning whoſe Auſterities, there are highly remarkable In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtances to be produced, in the Lives of <hi>Epictetus</hi> among the <hi>Sto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>icks,</hi> and <hi>Plotinus</hi> among the <hi>Plato<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſts.</hi> Though it may ſeem more conſiderable, perhaps, to inſtance in the Emperor <hi>Julian</hi> the Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtate; a man of high Birth, and great Power at laſt, and conſequent<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly much expoſed to Temptations of Luxury and Softneſs; who yet to the laſt, we are told, was wont to lye upon a hard courſe Quilt, and riſe continually in the middle of the night; to forbid all Delicacies to be brought into his Camp, and to feed upon the <hi>Common Soldiers</hi> Proviſions; which things he him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf glories in, and profeſſes to have learned them from his <hi>Heathen Maſters.</hi> Now the <hi>Primitive Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtians</hi> being to Converſe and Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpute with ſuch people as theſe, how could they more effectually recommend the Goſpel to them,
<pb n="103" facs="tcp:64677:60"/>than by ſhewing themſelves Exam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ples of like Severity with what they practiſed? Had they not done this, <hi>Chriſtianity</hi> would certainly have been thought as looſe and ſcanda<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lous a <hi>Profeſſion,</hi> as it was counted <hi>Fooliſh</hi> by theſe vain Pretenders to Wiſdom and Virtue. And confi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dering how mightily ſuch <hi>ſhews</hi> of Holineſs are apt to take among the <hi>Vulgar,</hi> the Philoſophers of thoſe times would have had the greateſt advantage by this means, of con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>firming the people in their <hi>Gentile</hi> Superſtitions, whilſt they compa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red their <hi>own</hi> lives, with the lives of the <hi>Chriſtians.</hi> And therefore in proceſs of time, when Perſecu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion being ceaſed, the <hi>Primitive Chriſtians</hi> began to allow them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves a greater <hi>Liberty</hi> about theſe things, we find the Apoſtate <hi>Ju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lian</hi> making it the great ſubject of his <hi>Raillery</hi> upon the <hi>Antiochians,</hi> (whom we muſt ſuppoſe to be ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nerally <hi>Chriſtians,</hi> by <hi>Nazianzen</hi>'s
<pb n="104" facs="tcp:64677:61"/>writing in their vindication), that the chief ground of their offence at him, was the Roughneſs of his Beard, and the Auſterity of his Life; that he <hi>made War</hi> continual<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly with his Belly, and delighted not in <hi>Dancing</hi> and <hi>Shows,</hi> as they did. And it is to the ſame pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe what he tells us of <hi>Conſtantine the Great,</hi> the firſt Chriſtian Em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peror, that finding none among the gods like himſelf, and ſo fit for him to converſe with, he betook himſelf to <hi>Luxury</hi> and <hi>Intempe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rance,</hi> as his <hi>Tutelar</hi> Deities, with whom he lived very contentedly; and recommended his Sons after<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards to their care. A little inno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cent freedom, we muſt think, in the <hi>Primitive Chriſtians,</hi> was e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nough to occaſion ſuch malicious Reflections from their Adverſaries: And this made it neceſſary for them to depart from their Right (as it were) in this reſpect; and to ſtrain the Bow not a little the other way,
<pb n="105" facs="tcp:64677:61"/>that their Enemies might have no pretence (if poſſible) to <hi>ſpeak re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>proachfully</hi> of them or their Reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gion.</p>
            <p n="31">31. But then our Saviour did not deſign that his Church ſhould continue in the <hi>Wilderneſs</hi> always; and God no more envies a <hi>Canaan</hi> of Worldly Felicity to us, than he did of old to his people the <hi>Jews.</hi> The <hi>Primitive Chriſtians</hi> Examples are certainly an excellent Argu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment for whetting peoples Indu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtry, and provoking Emulation: For if they endured ſo great hardſhip for the ſake of <hi>Chriſt,</hi> it is a great ſhame for men now-a-days to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fuſe Obedience to the more eaſie and rational Precepts of the Goſpel. But <hi>Chriſt</hi>'s Example is the only <hi>obligatory</hi> Pattern to us; and ſince we find nothing <hi>there</hi> of thoſe Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſterities which the <hi>Primitive Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtians</hi> obſerved, we have little rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon ſure, by adding theſe of our
<pb n="106" facs="tcp:64677:62"/>own accord,
<note place="margin">Mat. 11.30.</note> to make Chriſt's <hi>eaſie yoke</hi> heavier than he deſigned. There were <hi>ſpecial</hi> Reaſons, we ſee, that moved God's Providence to incline the <hi>Primitive Chriſtians</hi> to do what they did of this nature, which are now ceaſed in a great meaſure: For God be praiſed, we live not in ſuch an Age as they did, where our Lives, our Liberties, and Eſtates, are in danger of being taken from us every minute; but theſe are guarded by Laws, and ſecured to us by a Wonderful Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vidence; and there is no reaſon we ſhould deſpiſe ſuch a Bleſſing as this, but uſe that with Comfort, and Thanks to God, which he has given us to enjoy in Safety. Nor do we live among ſuch perſons whom we ought to <hi>conſider,</hi> as the <hi>Primitive Chriſtians</hi> did the <hi>Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thens,</hi> leſt they take offence at our <hi>juſt Liberty:</hi> For if any are offend<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed amongſt us, it is their own fault, having the Scriptures in their hands
<pb n="107" facs="tcp:64677:62"/>to read (which the <hi>Heathen</hi> had not) to inform them better. Thoſe Scriptures which will teach them, either that a greater Liberty is al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowed by Chriſt than the <hi>Primitive Chriſtians</hi> uſed, or at leaſt that they ought not to think the worſe of Religion for other mens failings in it; nor yet to cenſure and condemn others for taking greater freedom than themſelves approve of, unleſs they can plainly make it out to be contrary to the Precepts of the Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpel. To abſtain from little <hi>Indiffe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rent</hi> things, rather than offend our weak Brother, is certainly a very reaſonable Duty: But in ſuch things as theſe, which affect the <hi>whole Courſe</hi> of our lives, and are of mighty concern to the good of men, if other mens Weakneſs, and not the Scriptures, muſt be a Rule of walking to us, it will be impoſſible to know where to fix our Duty. Thus I think the Ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jection about the Primitive Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtians
<pb n="108" facs="tcp:64677:63"/>Example is ſufficiently an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwered.</p>
            <p n="32">32. Another Objection that may be made againſt this Diſcourſe is, That our Saviour's Doctrine, as it is contained in the Hiſtory of his Life, is not a ſufficient meaſure of Perfection, and therefore not fit to be propoſed <hi>by it ſelf</hi> as a Rule of Life; becauſe our Saviour in many things condeſcended to his Diſciples Weakneſs, leading them by Pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cepts ſuited to their <hi>Infant</hi> Eſtate, as they were yet but <hi>Novices</hi> in Religion; and reſerving others of a more <hi>ſublime</hi> nature for after<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>times, when the Spirit being pour<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed out in extraordinary meaſures, they were more advanced in Know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge and the fear of God: Which may ſeem to be implied in that <hi>Say<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing</hi> of our Saviour's to his Diſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ples,
<note place="margin">John 16.12.</note> 
               <hi>I have yet many things to ſay unto you, but ye cannot bear them now; howbeit, when he, the Spirit of Truth,
<pb n="109" facs="tcp:64677:63"/>is come, he will guide you into all truth.</hi> But that this is no Objection againſt us, will eaſily be made appear, when we conſider in the firſt place, that the ſubſtance of it is falſe and groundleſs in it ſelf, as far as it re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lates to matters of Practice gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rally neceſſary to Salvation, with which alone we have to do. For it is plain, our Saviour preſcribes Practical Doctrines to his Diſciples, of as great <hi>Perfection</hi> as any con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tained in his Religion: Such is that of <hi>cutting off their right hands,
<note place="margin">Mat. 5.29, 30.</note> and pulling out their right eyes when they offended them:</hi> Such is that of <hi>lo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving their enemies,
<note place="margin">— 44.</note> and doing good to them that hated them.</hi> Such, laſtly,
<note place="margin">Mat. 16.24.</note> is that of <hi>taking up their croſs, and forſaking father and mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, life and eſtate,</hi> for the Goſpel. For I think there is no greater Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gument of the <hi>Perfection</hi> of any Precept, than the Difficulty of it; as is evidently implied in that <hi>Say<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing</hi> of our Saviour's to the <hi>young
<pb n="110" facs="tcp:64677:64"/>man,
<note place="margin">Mat. 19.21.</note> If thou wilt be perfect, go ſell that thou haſt, and give it to the poor.</hi> And I am ſure there are no Precepts in the Goſpel more difficult than theſe; and therefore had our Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viour thought his Diſciples unfit to bear any Doctrines of a Practical nature, no queſtion but he would have concealed theſe as ſoon as any others, being the moſt likely to diſcourage his Diſciples from following him: Beſides that no greater <hi>Perfection</hi> can be ſuppoſed, than thoſe <hi>Sayings</hi> of our Saviour's to his Diſciples do expreſly enjoin, That they ſhould be <hi>holy as God is holy,
<note place="margin">Mat. 5.48.</note> and perfect as their heavenly Father is perfect.</hi> Wherefore alſo that <hi>Paſſage</hi> of St. <hi>John</hi> muſt neceſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſarily be interpreted to refer only to ſome extraordinary matters which concerned the Oeconomy of <hi>Chriſt</hi>'s Church in thoſe times: Such was the <hi>calling in</hi> of the <hi>Gentiles;</hi> a matter that the Apoſtles were ſo hardly brought to believe, that it
<pb n="111" facs="tcp:64677:64"/>required a ſpecial Revelation from God to aſcertain it to them. Such alſo was the Aboliſhing the Cere<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monial Law of <hi>Moſes,</hi> which occa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſioned ſuch violent Conteſts for a long time in the Church. Theſe indeed were things that we may ſuppoſe the Apoſtles ill able to bear, at the time our Saviour ſpoke, as being poſſeſſed with ſtrong Prejudi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces againſt them from their youth up: And it might well require an extraordinary Effuſion of the Spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit to <hi>guide them into ſuch Truths,</hi> which after all, they could ſcarce be perſuaded to believe. This In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terpretation is the rather to be re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceived, becauſe our Saviour tells his Diſciples in the foregoing Chapter,
<note place="margin">John 15.15.</note> that he had <hi>made known unto them all things that he had heard of his Father;</hi> it being very hard to reconcile this with the other place, if by <hi>all things</hi> here, is not to be meant all things neceſſary to Salvation.</p>
            <pb n="112" facs="tcp:64677:65"/>
            <p n="33">33. A Third and laſt Objection that I ſhall mention, againſt this Diſcourſe, may be drawn from thoſe places of Scripture wherein the ways of Salvation are repreſent<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed as very difficult, and hard to be found; particularly, that <hi>Saying</hi> of our Saviour's, where he exhorts his Diſciples <hi>to ſtrive to enter in at the ſtrait gate,
<note place="margin">Mat. 7.13, 14.</note> becauſe narrow is the way that leadeth to life, and few there be that find it:</hi> This ſeeming contrary to what is intimated all along in this Diſcourſe; the main drift of which has been, to make Religion appear eaſie and natural to men. Now to anſwer this Obje<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction, our chief buſineſs will be to reconcile this <hi>Saying</hi> of our Savi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>our's with that other of his, where he declares his <hi>yoak to be eaſie, and his burden light;</hi> this laſt making no leſs <hi>for</hi> every thing I have ſaid, than the other does <hi>againſt</hi> it. And it will be no hard matter to do this, by conſidering, That <hi>Chriſt</hi>'s Yoke
<pb n="113" facs="tcp:64677:65"/>is indeed eaſie <hi>in it ſelf;</hi> the Pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cepts of his Religion are no other than ſuch as men aſſiſted by God's Grace may even with Comfort and Pleaſure perform. But as the eaſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eſt Yoak may become <hi>hard</hi> by fretting and ſtriving againſt it; ſo <hi>Chriſt</hi>'s Religion is made difficult to men, through Prejudices and evil Habits, which put them upon endeavours of ſhaking it off, the better to ſatisfie ſome unruly Paſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons and Luſts, which gain the do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minion over them. And this is that alone which <hi>ſtraitens</hi> the Gate to Heaven; this makes the way thither ſeem rough, and melancho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, and deſolate, a <hi>very Wilderneſs</hi> to many that tread therein. Other<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe, far be it from God to delight himſelf in ſeeing men ſtruggling with difficulties which he himſelf has made. He that courts and im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>portunes us to come to Happineſs ſo earneſtly as he does, what an odd Notion of him muſt it imply,
<pb n="114" facs="tcp:64677:66"/>to make the means of attaining this <hi>hard;</hi> as if he deſigned it on pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe that few might arrive at it? No, there are no Difficulties in the way to Heaven, but what we make to our ſelves by our own groſs fault. Without this, the Road to Heaven would be as void of <hi>Briars and Thorns,</hi> as Heaven it ſelf is; <hi>The ways of wiſdom being ways of pleaſantneſs,</hi> as <hi>Solomon</hi> ſpeaks, <hi>and all her paths are peace:</hi> But then the Difficulties which men have brought upon themſelves in the ways of Godlineſs, through their own Corruptions, are certainly none of the leaſt: And theſe are ſuch as the greateſt Pretenders to Perfection may find abundant cauſe to be ſenſible of, tho they aim at nothing higher than what is pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcribed in this Diſcourſe: For even to be Juſt and Righteous in our Dealings, Chaſte in our Actions and Thoughts, Humble and Cha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritable in our Converſations, (if
<pb n="115" facs="tcp:64677:66"/>we conſult Experience, and not the nature of the things them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves) are not ſuch eaſie Duties, but that many who reckon them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves great Proficients in Grace, are found notoriouſly to fail in them. At leaſt, there are few, it's to be feared, that make a Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcience of theſe or any other Du<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties, ſo far as they ought in reaſon to do. And therefore conſidering the Hypocriſy of the world on one hand, and the too groſs Immorali<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty of it on the other, it were well if there were not too great grounds for that <hi>Saying</hi> of our Saviour, That <hi>narrow is the way to life, and few there be that find it.</hi> Though ſtill it is to be hoped, the Few there mentioned are no inconſiderable Number, only as oppoſed to the vaſt Company of <hi>Jews, Turks, In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fidels,</hi> and Prophane perſons, who proudly deſpiſe the Means of Sal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vation which Chriſt has offered to them. And for thoſe who have a
<pb n="116" facs="tcp:64677:67"/>Saviour to truſt in, and a Merciful God to fly to, who make allowan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces for the common Infirmities of Human Nature, we truſt that a wide Gate of Salvation may be opened to ſuch, as long as with Faith and Sincerity they endeavour to walk in the way of God's Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mands, and pretend not to <hi>act</hi> the Cripple before him.</p>
            <p n="34">34. Wherefore, in ſhort, the Sum of this Diſcourſe is, That the Religion of Chriſt, according to his Precepts and Example (and we need no better Rule to judge of it by) is a moſt admirably Wiſe, Gra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cious, and Manlike Religion; ſuch as <hi>accompliſhes</hi> Human Nature in the higheſt degrees it is capable of in this life; impoſing nothing mean or ſervile upon us: Such as looks upon Ceremonies only as things in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>different; neither refuſing what is Decent, or commanded by juſt Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thority, nor yet encouraging Vain
<pb n="117" facs="tcp:64677:67"/>or Superſtitious Obſervancies: Such as commends a Sober and a Ratio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nal Piety to us; a Piety that con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiſts not in high Notions, or wild Expreſſions of Zeal, but in Wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhipping and Serving God with Diligence and Sincerity: Such as <hi>takes off</hi> from the Exorbitancies of our Paſſions and Luſts, ſo as to make us moſt eaſie to our ſelves, and moſt like to God, without de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>barring us the innocent Comforts of this life. Such, laſtly, as enga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges us to be good natured, and to throw off thoſe ſelfiſh and unnatu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ral Diſpoſitions, which are the Ruin of Society, and a Reproach to Mankind: Than which, as I think there can no <hi>Ideas</hi> of Reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gion be framed more Excellent, ſo let us ſtudy to conform our Lives to theſe, and I queſtion not but we become <hi>True</hi> Followers of <hi>Chriſt Jeſus.</hi>
            </p>
         </div>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:64677:68"/>
            <pb n="119" facs="tcp:64677:68"/>
            <p>AN APPENDIX Concerning the HYPOCRISY OF THE <hi>PHARISEES.</hi>
            </p>
         </div>
         <div type="appendix">
            <pb facs="tcp:64677:69"/>
            <pb n="121" facs="tcp:64677:69"/>
            <head>AN APPENDIX Concerning the <hi>Hypocriſy of the Phariſees.</hi>
            </head>
            <p>THOUGH Hypocriſy be often objected by our Saviour againſt the <hi>Pha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſees,</hi> yet I could never be of the opinion, That they were <hi>groſs downright</hi> Hypocrites; ſuch, I mean, as take a <hi>Form of Godlineſs</hi> upon them, only for Secular Inte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reſt, to ſerve deſigns of Knavery and Injuſtice, and who know them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves to be Hypocrites all the while. I have ſo much Charity for Human Nature, as to hope there are few ſuch Creatures as
<pb n="122" facs="tcp:64677:70"/>theſe in the World; theſe being but one Remove from <hi>Atheiſts:</hi> For ſure, did men believe that there was a God who governed the world, they durſt never affront him ſo directly, as to make uſe of his Name and Religion to cloak the moſt profligate Deſigns. The great<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eſt <hi>Impoſtors</hi> in the world, I be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieve, may have acted out of Prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciples of Conſcience: And I take <hi>Mahomet</hi> himſelf to have had much more of the Enthuſiaſt in him, than the Hypocrite. Nor ought it to be thought ſtrange, that ſuch horrid Doctrines and Practices as many of theſe have been the <hi>Authors</hi> of, ſhould be the effects of a good In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tention: For there is nothing ſo ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſurd, which a crazed head, or vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiated underſtanding will not be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieve to be right ſometimes. With what ſtrange Aſſurance will ſome Madmen fancy themſelves Kings and Emperours, and not be beaten out of their Conceit by all that
<pb n="123" facs="tcp:64677:70"/>men can ſay; but turn even their Rags and their Chains, and every thing elſe that can be objected to them, into <hi>Enſigns</hi> of Majeſty. It is the ſame unhappy Influence that rules in the heads of moſt Enthuſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>aſts. And though the Heads of ſome of them may not be turned at this rate, yet there are many ways of debauching Conſcience, and ſtifling <hi>Natural Light</hi> in ſuch; and when ſtrong Affections and Luſts meet with weak or prejudi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ced Judgments, it is no hard mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter for <hi>ſuch</hi> to perſwade themſelves by degrees into the belief of what<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ever almoſt they pleaſe. It was certainly a moſt perverſe piece of Stupidity in the <hi>Jews,</hi> after all the Miracles and Good Works that our Saviour wrought among them, to believe him worthy to be Crucified at laſt:
<note place="margin">Luke 23.34.</note> And yet our Saviour him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf imputes this groſſeſt of Crimes to Weakneſs, and not to Malice; and St. <hi>Peter</hi> in ſome meaſure ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cuſes,
<pb n="124" facs="tcp:64677:71"/>not only the People, but their <hi>Rulers</hi> alſo,
<note place="margin">Act. 3.17.</note> upon this ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>count: Of ſuch ſtrange force were the Prejudices of Education, Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour, and Worldly Intereſt, for perverting the Underſtandings of theſe men. But if in ſuch a caſe as this, men could refuſe to hearken to the ſtrongeſt Evidences of Rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon and Senſe, no wonder that in any other caſe they can <hi>ſtop their ears to the voice of the charmer, charm he never ſo wiſely.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="2">2. That the <hi>Phariſees</hi> did real<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly act in the main upon Principles of Religion and Conſcience, we have good ground to think, when we conſider that Character our Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viour gives of them, That they were ſpiritually proud, and ſtrange<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly opinionative of their Righteouſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs; by which they fancied they could merit Salvation at God's hands:
<note place="margin">Luke 18.11.</note> As we find one of them therefore juſtifying himſelf before
<pb n="125" facs="tcp:64677:71"/>God in the Temple; and another very confidently telling our Savi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>our,
<note place="margin">Mat. 19.20.</note> That he had <hi>kept all the com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mandments from his youth up:</hi> For ſure it is impoſſible to think that men who ſerve not God with Sin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerity, ſhould flatter themſelves at this rate into opinions of their Righteouſneſs; eſpecially, that ſuch opinions ſhould ſtick by them at the Day of Judgment: As our Saviour plainly points at this ſort of men, when he tells us,
<note place="margin">Mat. 7.22.</note> That <hi>many ſhall come to him at that day, and ſay, Lord, have we not prophecied in thy name, and in thy name caſt out devils, and in thy name done many wondrous works?</hi> For how abſurd is it to think, that Hypocrites can have the Impudence to plead at this rate before <hi>Chriſt,</hi> at ſuch a time when they cannot but be ſenſible the thoughts of their hearts are all o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pen and revealed to him? With<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out doubt the utmoſt ſhame and confuſion of face ſhall belong to
<pb n="126" facs="tcp:64677:72"/>ſuch then: Such are conſcious to themſelves of their own Wicked<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs; they know that what good things they did in this life, were not done in Sincerity of heart; and it is not a fit time ſurely <hi>then</hi> to urge thoſe things in their Vindica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, which being done in Hypo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>criſy, have been condemned long ſince with the ſevereſt Sentence by their Judge: Nor can I well per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceive the force of that Declaration of our Saviour's,
<note place="margin">Mat 5.20.</note> 
               <hi>Except your righ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teouſneſs exceed the righteouſneſs of the Scribes and Phariſees, you ſhall in no caſe enter into the kingdom of heaven;</hi> if the <hi>Phariſees</hi> were downright Hypocrites: For what a mighty buſineſs is this, that <hi>Chriſt</hi> ſhould require the Righte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſneſs of his Diſciples to be great<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er than that of thoſe who were lit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tle better than <hi>Atheiſts?</hi> Who were all falſe and impious at bottom; who had nothing in them of that Holineſs they pretended to? Who
<pb n="127" facs="tcp:64677:72"/>does not perceive the ſmall <hi>Empha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſis,</hi> or rather Vanity of ſuch a De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>claration? Beſides, that our Savi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>our's after-Diſcourſe is a plain <hi>Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment</hi> upon this Text; wherein he ſhews his meaning to be, That his Diſciples Righteouſneſs ought to exceed the <hi>Phariſees</hi> Righteouſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs, not in <hi>Sincerity,</hi> but in <hi>Perfe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction</hi> of Obedience: And <hi>that</hi> by ſpiritualizing the Law of <hi>Moſes,</hi> and reforming thoſe Corruptions which the <hi>Scribes</hi> and <hi>Phariſees</hi> had brought into it by their <hi>Tradi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="3">3. Nor is it a ſufficient Argu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment againſt this, That our Saviour deſcribes the <hi>Phariſees</hi> ſo often by the Character of <hi>groſs</hi> Hypocrites; as that they <hi>did all things to be ſeen of men;</hi>
               <note place="margin">Mat. 23.5 Mat. 23.27. Luk. 11.44. Mat. 23.14.</note> that they were <hi>whited ſepul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chres, and graves which appeared not;</hi> that <hi>for a pretence they made long prayers.</hi> For it is uſual in Scripture for God to judge other<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe
<pb n="128" facs="tcp:64677:73"/>of mens actions, than they themſelves think or deſign: And if in outward appearance any action be vicious, and ſo of bad Example, God will take it many times in the <hi>worſt</hi> ſenſe, and impute it as done on purpoſe, and of malice, though there were no ſuch thing in the perſon's Intentions. Thus in the caſe of Idolatry, God tells the <hi>Iſra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>elites,</hi> That they worſhipped <hi>ſtocks and ſtones</hi> for their God,
<note place="margin">Iſa. 44.17.</note> and cried to thoſe ſenſeleſs things for help; whereas indeed it was only in out<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward appearance they did this; and they worſhipped God all this while under the <hi>Similitude</hi> of thoſe Graven Images they fell down be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore. Thus alſo men are ſaid in Scripture <hi>to deny God,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Prov. 30.7. Phil. 3.19.</note> and to make <hi>gods</hi> of their <hi>bellies</hi> and their <hi>wealth,</hi> when they ſerve thoſe chiefly; not that they disbelieve the true God, or think their bellies and their wealth to be <hi>gods</hi> really; but only that their outward actions look as
<pb n="129" facs="tcp:64677:73"/>if their inward thoughts were of this nature: In like manner as the <hi>Phariſees</hi> are ſtiled Hypocrites by our Saviour; not as tho they were ſuch in a ſtrict ſenſe of the word, but becauſe they acted <hi>like</hi> Hypo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crites. Their Religion indeed was juſt ſuch a ſort of Religion, as we may ſuppoſe that of Hypocrites would be; a Religion that buſied it ſelf only about ſuch Duties as were moſt apt to gain Applauſe and Admiration from the world; ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king light of other matters that were of no leſs weight in them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves: Such a Religion, as taught them to make <hi>long prayers,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Mat. 23.14. Mat. 7.12. Mat. 23.23.</note> but to <hi>devour widows houſes;</hi> to give <hi>gifts</hi> to the Temple, but to let their <hi>Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rents</hi> ſtarve; to be very ſober in their Coverſations, but falſe and cruel in their Dealings; to talk Scripture much, but to be proud and uncharitable in their Applica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions of it. In ſhort, for what there was of it, their Religion
<pb n="130" facs="tcp:64677:74"/>was <hi>ſincere</hi> enough; and it was not of direct intent, but by accident only, that their Piety and Tempe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rance proved ſuch a cloak for their Knavery and Oppreſſion. But in regard mens Credulity was as much abuſed by their Sanctified Behavi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>our, as if they had deſigned it on purpoſe to <hi>draw them in;</hi> and Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligion was no leſs ſcandalized by it; therefore does our Saviour in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terpret all they did, of downright Hypocriſy.</p>
            <p n="4">4. I confeſs we read of one ſort of <hi>Phariſees,</hi> that were called <hi>Si<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chemite Phariſees,</hi> becauſe they were ſuppoſed to take that <hi>Profeſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion</hi> upon themſelves for worldly advantage; as <hi>Sichem</hi> Circumciſed himſelf for the ſake of <hi>Dinah:</hi> But then theſe were but one Sect among ſeven of them, that <hi>Druſius</hi> rec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kons up; and theſe of ſo ſmall e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſteem among their own Party, as well as among the People, compa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red
<pb n="131" facs="tcp:64677:74"/>with the reſt, that they cannot reaſonably be ſuppoſed to include the main <hi>Body</hi> of the <hi>Phariſees,</hi> whom our Saviour calls Hypocrites without diſtinction. Beſides that ſuppoſing theſe to be groſs Hypo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crites, this ſtrongly implies the o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther Sects not to have been ſo; the Exception confirming the Rule: Nor could our Saviour therefore in juſtice fix this Character of Hy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pocrites upon the <hi>Phariſees,</hi> on ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>count of <hi>theſe alone,</hi> whilſt there were ſo many Sects among them that deſerved it not; no more than a <hi>Jew</hi> or <hi>Turh,</hi> ſuppoſe, can with juſt reaſon charge <hi>Chriſtians</hi> as being generally <hi>Atheiſts,</hi> tho there are many of them in the world, whoſe words and actions give too great occaſion for ſuch a Scandal: And ſtill there is nothing that has been ſaid about the <hi>Phariſees</hi> in <hi>general,</hi> but is as applicable to <hi>theſe,</hi> as any others: For tho Worldly Advan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tage was the great thing they mind<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed,
<pb n="132" facs="tcp:64677:75"/>and ſo their Religion <hi>ſeemed</hi> but a Pretence; yet no queſtion but they might ſatisfie their Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſciences in this with moſt Hypo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crites now-a days, That whatever others might think of them, God's Glory <hi>indeed</hi> was the main thing they aimed at in their Practice of Religion; and if they throve and proſpered by this, if men admired them for their Religious Strict<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſes, and Worldly Profit flowed in by ſuch means, this was none of their fault, they might ſay; rather it was the peculiar Bleſſing of God to them, for their Love and Fear of his Name.</p>
            <p n="5">5. And we have leſs reaſon to wonder, that the <hi>Phariſees</hi> could ſatisfie their Conſciences in the Pra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctice of ſuch groſs ſins as our Savi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>our charges them with, when we conſider that odd Maxim, that is reported to have been generally re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceived by the <hi>Jewiſh Doctors,</hi> viz.
<pb n="133" facs="tcp:64677:75"/>That it is neceſſary for every man to beſtow his Diligence more eſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cially about ſome one Precept of the Law; and that if he be faithful and ſucceſsful in this, it is enough to atone for his Tranſgreſſions of all other Duties: For by this the <hi>Pha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſees</hi> had liberty to chuſe or let a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lone what Commandments they thought fit: And they might well think it a notable pitch of Perfe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction to be careful in obſerving the <hi>better half</hi> of their Law, (as they did) when the keeping <hi>one ſingle</hi> Precept was ſo Meritorious before God. Now the <hi>Phariſees</hi> darling ſins were Covetouſneſs and Pride; and to ſecure themſelves in the qui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>et poſſeſſion of theſe, there were no Duties they could better ſpare, in way of <hi>Compoſition</hi> with God, than Piety and Temperance. Piety (ſuch as theirs was) ſerving them with many opportunies for grati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fying their Pride; and Temperance being a <hi>frugal</hi> Virtue, which <hi>regu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lated
<pb n="134" facs="tcp:64677:76"/>Expences,</hi> for obliging their Covetouſneſs: And therefore, leſt an ordinary practice of ſuch Duties might not make the <hi>Merit</hi> of them ſufficient, they were willing to raiſe the Value of them by extraor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinary Strictneſſes:
<note place="margin">Mat 9 14.</note> They <hi>prayed long</hi> therefore, and faſted often, and made a mighty buſtle <hi>in waſhing pans and cups,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Mark 7.4. Luk. 11.42.</note> and <hi>tithing Mint and Cummin,</hi> to make their Piety more compleat; and ſo over-ſcrupulous were they (we have heard) in their Rules of Temperance, that they could faſten the Names of Wine-bibber and Glutton even up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on our Saviour. To which Duties they added a ſevere abſtinence from Laſcivious Acts, as things of ſo ſcandalous a nature, they knew, that one trip in theſe was enough to ruin their Reputation, by which their Pride and Covetouſneſs were maintained. Nor do I think it a contemptible Argument of the <hi>Phariſees</hi> Sincerity in theſe Duties,
<pb n="135" facs="tcp:64677:76"/>that our Saviour no where con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demns them for any ſecret failings in them: For Hypocrites, who deſign only a <hi>ſhew</hi> of Religion, value not what ſins they commit in <hi>private:</hi> But our Saviour, who knew the <hi>Pha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſees</hi> hearts much better than they themſelves did, does in a great mea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure acquit them of this, by object<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing no ſuch thing againſt them. The only conſiderable place unmention<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed that I know, relating to <hi>this,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Mat. 23 3, 4.</note> is that <hi>Saying</hi> of his, That the <hi>Phari ſees ſaid, and did not; and that they bound heavy burdens upon mens ſhoul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders, which they themſelves would not touch with one of their fingers:</hi> But this plainly refers, not to their inward thoughts, but their out<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward acts; as is evident from our Saviour's commanding his Diſciples there, not to do after their works; and ſo is no proof of ſuch Hypocri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſy being in them, as I have been ſpeaking of: And indeed all of this nature that can be concluded direct<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly
<pb n="136" facs="tcp:64677:77"/>from this place, is only, That the <hi>Phariſees ſitting in Moſes's ſeat,</hi> and ſo being Doctors of the Law, preſſed many Duties of Religion upon the <hi>People,</hi> which they them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves practiſed not: But ſure, however reprovable the Miniſters or Governors of any Church are, for not obſerving thoſe Duties they teach; yet ought they not to be looked upon always as Hypocrites for this; many not having Grace to practiſe thoſe things they teach, though they may believe them ſin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerely enough to be right; and eſpecially ſuch as theſe being obliged by virtue of their Office to inculcate the Duties of Religion upon others, whatever their own failings may be. And therefore, though our Saviour condemns the <hi>Phariſees</hi> in this place, for <hi>laying heavy burdens upon mens ſhoulders, which themſelves would not touch;</hi> this argues not the Hypocriſy, but the vanity and unreaſonableneſs of
<pb n="137" facs="tcp:64677:77"/>their Doctrines, in ſtraining the Duties of Religion to impractica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble heights, and condemning others uncharitably for every leſſer ſlip, when themſelves were daily guilty of much greater Crimes.</p>
            <p n="6">6. Wherefore, in fine, a man may be a Hypocrite, I think, tho he knows it not himſelf; and it is not only to <hi>deſign</hi> contrary to his Profeſſions of Holineſs, but to <hi>do</hi> contrary to them, that ranks him among ſuch perſons: And this I take to be the nature of the <hi>Phari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſees</hi> Hypocriſy: The <hi>Phariſees</hi> were ſuch perſons as wiſe <hi>Agur</hi> ſpeaks of,
<note place="margin">Prov. 30.12.</note> who were <hi>pure in their own eyes, and yet were not waſhed from their fil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thineſs:</hi> Men that appeared not on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly to others, but to themſelves, very Righteous perſons: And they had no ſmall reaſon to think <hi>thus</hi> of themſelves, had Piety and Tempe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rance, and the like Duties, been the only things required of us by God: But their great fault was,
<pb n="138" facs="tcp:64677:78"/>that reſting altogether in Perfor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mances of this nature, they be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>came careleſs of other Duties no leſs neceſſary to Salvation; ſuch more eſpecially are thoſe that are called <hi>Social</hi> Vertues: For they ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>glected thoſe <hi>weighty matters of the Law</hi> (our Saviour ſays) <hi>Judgment,
<note place="margin">Mat. 23.23.</note> Mercy, and Faith;</hi> where by Judg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, he means Juſtice; by Mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cy, Charity; by Faith, Faithful<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs in dealing; by all of theſe, the whole of our Duty towards our Neighbour: Theſe the <hi>Phari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſees</hi> made little account of, as Du<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties of an inferior rank, which even Heathens and Sinners (for ſo their Spiritual Pride prompted them to call every one almoſt that was not of their own Sect) pra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctiſed. But whatever the <hi>Phari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſees</hi> might think of ſuch Duties,
<note place="margin">Mat. 22.36.</note> our Saviour looks upon them as no other than the one half of Religi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on; and this of ſuch eſteem in his ſight, that the moſt ſpecious Holi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs
<pb n="139" facs="tcp:64677:78"/>was but as a piece of <hi>Pagean<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>try</hi> and <hi>mock ſhew</hi> with him, when ſuch <hi>ſubſtantial</hi> Duties were ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>glected. It is by theſe therefore, that he has taught us to know Hy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pocrites, as <hi>by their fruits;</hi>
               <note place="margin">Mat. 7.16.</note> and by the ſame marks he himſelf judges of the <hi>Phariſees;</hi> becauſe theſe fruits of Righteouſneſs appeared not in their lives; but how fair or promiſing ſoever the Tree might ſeem, they were either wholly bar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ren in Good Works, or elſe produ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ced Fruits quite contrary to expe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctation, Fruits that were noxious and fatal to ſuch who converſed with them; therefore does our Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viour pronounce them to be Hypo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crites;
<note place="margin">Mat. 23.14.</note> therefore does he declare that they ſhall <hi>receive the greater damna<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion.</hi> And this Notion of the <hi>Pha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſees</hi> Hypocriſy, as I take it to be moſt juſt and true in it ſelf, ſo does it beſt agree with that common Notion we have of a <hi>Phariſaical Righteouſneſs;</hi> whereby we don't
<pb n="140" facs="tcp:64677:79"/>mean a <hi>Counterfeit</hi> one, but a vain and empty one, that conſiſts in <hi>forms of godlineſs, denying the power thereof;</hi> which ought to ſhew it ſelf in Good Works.</p>
            <p n="7">7. Nor ought this to be reckon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed a vain Subject of Diſcourſe now<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>a days; for though the <hi>Phariſees</hi> have long ſince been dead and rot<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten in their Graves, yet are their Principles and Practices ſtill ſtir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring among us; and there are ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny, it's to be ſeared, to whom the Name of a <hi>Phariſee</hi> is ſufficiently odious, who yet, by miſtaking the Nature of the <hi>Phariſees</hi> Hypocri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſy, reckon it a great Perfection in Religion to imitate them in their moſt <hi>diſtinguiſhing</hi> Qualities: For we live in an Age wherein the greateſt Pretenders to Religion are ſo taken up with <hi>ſhews</hi> of Holineſs, that they mind little elſe; ard this with no leſs Satisfaction to them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves, than Applauſe and Admira<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion
<pb n="141" facs="tcp:64677:79"/>from the people. Inſomuch, that if <hi>Chriſt</hi> were to appear again upon earth with thoſe innocent freedoms he allowed himſelf in here, and a ſtrict <hi>Phariſee</hi> at the ſame time, with <hi>long prayers,</hi> and a <hi>face disfigured,</hi> and eye-lids conti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nually lift up, and a brow knit at every little liberty men took, (tho without offence to God), it is little to be queſtioned, if ſome were to be the Judges, which would be reckoned the greater <hi>Saint</hi> of the two. Our Saviour's Modeſty and Good Works would in all likeli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hood weigh as little among ſuch, for turning the ſcale on his ſide, as the <hi>Phariſees</hi> Pride and Injuſtice would hinder it from turning the other way. Such ſins as theſe being reckoned at worſt but ſpecks in God's Children, which God will not be extreme to mark; and ſuch therefore as ſhall make a better ſhow among ſome people, when gilded over by a ſpecious Holineſs,
<pb n="142" facs="tcp:64677:80"/>than the Virtues of other men, whoſe Converſations are not alto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gether ſo Formal. As long as ſuch Principles and Practices as theſe are thus <hi>taking</hi> in the world, it cannot certainly be unſeaſonable to ſhew the dangerouſneſs of them; which I think ſufficiently appears in this Caſe of the <hi>Phariſees;</hi> for it was theſe chiefly, we ſee, that occaſioned thoſe many <hi>Woes</hi> which our Saviour pronounces againſt them. They contented themſelves with a half<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>face Religion, which looked fair towards God, but was full of Pride and the like Deformities on the o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther ſide, carrying Guile and Op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſion in it towards their Neigh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bour. And our Saviour is ſo far from approving this, that he looks upon them as no other than Hypo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crites for it. So odious in his eſteem were theſe Vices of theirs, which many make ſo light of, that not their Faſtings and Prayers, not their Attendance upon Ordinances, not
<pb n="143" facs="tcp:64677:80"/>all their Zeal and Strictneſſes in other parts of Religion, could re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>commend them to one good word from him, when attended with ſuch Moral Defects as theſe. Cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tainly a plain Argument of the Excellency of Moral Precepts; and ſuch as might be ſufficient to make thoſe aſhamed who upbraid our Church with inſiſting upon ſuch Precepts, and pretend to make di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtinctions betwixt Preaching Chriſt and theſe: As if to Preach Chriſt, were any thing elſe than to Preach thoſe Duties which Chriſt has com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>manded; and as if there were any Duties that are urged upon mens Practice by Chriſt, under more preſſing Circumſtances than theſe. Tho God forbid here, that I ſhould be thought any ways to vilifie the Duties of <hi>real</hi> Piety, ſo as to prefer Moral Duties before them, much leſs to reckon them of ſmall weight in themſelves: For when all is done, To Love the Lord our God
<pb n="144" facs="tcp:64677:81"/>with <hi>all our heart and all our ſouls,
<note place="margin">Mat. 22.38.</note> is the firſt and great commandment.</hi> And this is that, under Chriſt, which ſanctifies every Moral work we do; Theſe being altogether vain and fruitleſs in the way to Sal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vation, when not acted with a de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſign of pleaſing God, and ſetting forth his Glory thereby: But what I have ſaid, is only to ſhew, That to Love our Neighbour as our ſelves, is that <hi>ſecond commandment which is like unto the firſt;</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Ibid.</hi> 39.</note> and that without doing this Will of our Heavenly Father, there is no en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tring into the Kingdom of God: For as our Saviour tells the <hi>Phari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſees</hi> in a ſomewhat parallel caſe, Tho the former ought to be done, this latter ought by no means to be left undone; and there is no leſs danger in omitting one than the other.</p>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
            <pb facs="tcp:64677:81"/>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
